<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Severall papers lately vvritten and published by Iudge Ienkins, prisoner in the Tower viz. 1. His vindication. 2. The armies indempnity [sic]: with a declaration, shewing, how every subject ought to be tryed for treasons, felonies, and all other capitall crimes. 3. Lex terræ. 4. A cordiall for the good people of London. 5. A discourse touching the incoveniences of a long continued Parliament. 6. An apologie for the army.</title>
            <title>Severall papers lately written and published by Judge Jenkins, prisoner in the Tower.</title>
            <author>Jenkins, David, 1582-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828737</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1968:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Severall papers lately vvritten and published by Iudge Ienkins, prisoner in the Tower viz. 1. His vindication. 2. The armies indempnity [sic]: with a declaration, shewing, how every subject ought to be tryed for treasons, felonies, and all other capitall crimes. 3. Lex terræ. 4. A cordiall for the good people of London. 5. A discourse touching the incoveniences of a long continued Parliament. 6. An apologie for the army.</title>
                  <title>Severall papers lately written and published by Judge Jenkins, prisoner in the Tower.</title>
                  <author>Jenkins, David, 1582-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, [2], 13, [1], 8, 7-30, [1], 14, [2], 10, [2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Judge Jenkins = David Jenkins.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>"The armies indemnity", "The cordiall of Judge Jenkins", "A discourse touching the incoveniencies", and "An apology for the army" have separate dated title pages, paginations and registers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jenkins, David, 1582-1663 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional law --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>SEVERALL PAPERS Lately VVritten and Publiſhed by IUDGE IENKINS, Priſoner in the Tower: <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>His Vindication.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Armies indempnity: with a Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhewing, how every Subject ought to be tryed for Treaſons, Felonies, and all other Capitall Crimes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Lex Terrae.</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>A Cordiall for the good people of London.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>A Diſcourſe touching the inconveniences of a long continued Parliament.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>An Apologie for the Army.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>ANNO 1647.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33168:2"/>
                  <head>The Vindication of Iudge <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the Tower, the 29. of Apr. 1647.</head>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <p>I Was convened upon Saturday the 10. of this moneth of Aprill before a Committee of the Houſe of Commons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Maſter <hi>Corbet</hi> had the Chaire; and I was there to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined upon ſome queſtions then to be propounded to me; to which queſtions I refuſed to give any other anſwer then that which was ſet down in a paper I then delivered to the ſaid M. <hi>Corbet,</hi> which followeth in theſe words:</p>
                        <p>Gentlemen, I ſtand committed by the Houſe of Commons for High Treaſon, for not acknowledging, nor obeying the power of the Two Houſes, by adhering to the King in this War. I deny this to be Treaſon, for the ſupreame and onely power, by the Lawes of this Land, is in the King. If I ſhould ſubmit to any exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination derived from your Power, which by the Negative Oath ſtands in oppoſition to the Kings Power, I ſhould confeſſe the Power to be in you, and ſo condemne my ſelfe for a Traitour, which I neither ought nor will doe.</p>
                        <p>I am ſworne to obey the King, and the Laws of this Land: you have not power to examine me by thoſe Laws, by the Kings Writ, Patent, or Commiſſion; if you can produce either thereof, I will anſwer the queſtions you ſhall propound; otherwiſe I cannot anſwer thereto, without the breach of my Oath, and the violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lawes, which I will not doe to ſave my life.</p>
                        <p>You your ſelves, all of you this Parliament, have ſworne that the King is our onely and ſupreame Governour: your Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, your Vow and Covenant, your ſolemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, your Declarations, all of them publiſh to the Kingdome, that your ſcope is the maintenance of the Lawes; thoſe Lawes are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33168:3"/>and muſt be derived to us, and enlivened by the only ſupreame Governour, the Fountaine of juſtice, and the life of the Law, the King. The Parliaments are called by his writs; the Judges ſit by his Pattents, ſo of all other Officers; the Cities and Towns cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, governe by the Kings Charters; and therefore ſince by the Law I cannot be examin'd by you, without a power derived by His Majeſty, I neither can, nor will, nor ought you to examine me upon any queſtion. But if as private Gentlemen, you ſhall be pleaſed to aske me any queſtions, I ſhall really and truly anſwer every ſuch queſtion, as you ſhall demand.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Aprill</hi> 10. 1647.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>David Jenkins.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>This paper hath been miſ-repreſented to the good people of this Citie by a Printed one, ſtyling it my Recantation, which I owne not; and beſides is in it ſelfe repugnant (juſt like theſe times) the Body falls out with the Head. To vindicate my ſelfe from that Recantation, and to publiſh to the world the realitie of the Paper then delivered to M. <hi>Corbet,</hi> and the matter therein contained, I have publiſhed this enſuing diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>No perſon who hath committed Treaſon, Murder, or Felony, hath any aſſurance at all for ſo much as one houre of life, Lands or Goods without the Kings gracious pardon, 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 24.</p>
                  <p>The King is not virtually in the two Houſes at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> whereby they may give any aſſurance at all to any perſon, in any thing, for any ſuch offence.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Houſe of Commons hath declared to the Kingdome in their Declarations of the 28. of <hi>November</hi> laſt to the <hi>Scots</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. <hi>That the King at this time is not in a condition to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne.</hi> No perſon or thing can derive a vertue to other men, or things, which it ſelfe hath not: and therefore it is impoſſible that they ſhould have a vertue from the King to governe, which they declare he hath not himſelfe to give.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">5. <hi>Elizab. Cap.</hi> 1.</note> The Law of the Land is, <hi>That no perſon in any Parliament hath a voice in the Houſe of Commons, but that he ſtands a perſon to all intents and purpoſes as if he had never beene elected or returned, if before he ſit in the Houſe, he take not his Oath upon the holy Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33168:3"/>that the Kings Majeſtie is the only and ſupream Governour over all perſons in all Cauſes.</hi> All the Members of the ſaid Houſe have taken it, and at all times as they are returned doe take it; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they have no colour to intermeddle with the publicke Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. How doth this Solemne and Legall Oath agree with their ſaid Declaration, <hi>That the King is in no condition to governe?</hi> By the one it is ſworne, He is the only ſupreame Governour; by the other, that he is not in a condition to governe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Oath is not, that the K. was, or ought to be, or had been, before he was ſeduced by ill Councell, our onely and ſupreame Governour in all Cauſes, over all perſons; but in the preſent tenſe, that he is our onely and ſupreame Governour, at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in all Cauſes and over all perſons. So they the ſame perſons ſweare one thing, and declare to the Kingdom the contrary of the ſame thing, at the ſame time, in that which concerneth the weale of all this Nation.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Miniſters in the Pulpits doe not ſay, what they ſweare in the Houſe of Commons. Whoever heard ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thence this unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Warre, any of their Presbyters attribute that to His Majeſtie which they ſweare? The reaſon is, their Oath is taken at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> amongſt themſelves: That which their Miniſters pray and preach, goes amongſt the people. To tell the people that the King is now their onely and ſupreame Governour in all Cauſes, is contrary to that the Houſes doe now practice, and to all they act and maintaine. They, the two Houſes forſooth, are the onely and ſupreame Governours in default of the King, for that he hath left his great Councell and will not come to them, and yet the King deſires to come, but they will not ſuffer him, but keepe him priſoner at <hi>Holmby:</hi> ſo well doe their Actions and Oathes agree.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. They ſweare now King CHARLES is their onely and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour; but with a reſolution at the time of the Oath taking, and before and after, that he ſhall not be onely or ſupreme Governour, or onely and ſupreme, but not any Governour at all: For there is no point of Government, but for ſome yeares paſt they have taken to themſelves, and uſed his name onely, to abuſe and deceive the people.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33168:4"/>
                  <p n="6">6. That this virtuall power is a meere fiction, their Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſent to <hi>Oxford,</hi> to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to be ſigned by the King, doe prove it ſo. What needs this adoe, if they have the virtuall power with them at <hi>Weſtminſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. To affirme that the Kings power (which is the virtue they talk of) is ſeparable from his Perſon, is High Treaſon by the Law of the Land; which is ſo declared by that learned man of the Law, Sir <hi>Edward Coke;</hi> ſo much magnified by this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; who in the 7. part of his Reports, in <hi>Calv.</hi> Caſe, fo. 11. ſaith thus: <hi>In the reigne of Edward the ſecond, the Spencers, the Father and Son, to cover the Treaſon hatched in their hearts, invented this damnable and damned opinion, that Homage and Oath of Ligeance was more by reaſon of the Kings Crowne, (that is, of his politicke ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity) then by reaſon of the perſon of the King: upon which opinion they inferred</hi> 3. <hi>execrable and deteſtable conſequences.</hi> 1. <hi>If the King doe not demeane himſelfe by reaſon in the right of his Crowne, his lieges are bound by Oath to remove the King.</hi> 2. <hi>ſeeing that the King could not be reformed by ſuit of Law, that ought to be done</hi> per aſpertee <hi>that is by force.</hi> 3. <hi>That his lieges be bound to governe in aid of him, and in default of him: All which were condemned by two Parliaments, one in the raigne of</hi> Edw, 2. <hi>called</hi> exilium Hugonis le Spencer; and the other in Anno 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>And that the naturall body and politicke makes one indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble body, and that theſe two bodies incorporate in one perſon make one body, and not divers, is reſolved as the Law of <hi>England.</hi> 4. <hi>Eliz. Ploydon</hi> Com. fol. 213. by Sir <hi>Cobert Catlin,</hi> Lord Chiefe Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>James Dier,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas, the Lord <hi>Sanders,</hi> Lord Chiefe Baron of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and by the reſt of the Judges, <hi>viz.</hi> Juſtice <hi>Raſtall,</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Browne,</hi> Juſtice <hi>Corbet,</hi> Juſtice <hi>Weſton,</hi> Baron <hi>Frevyll, Conne</hi> and <hi>Pewdrell,</hi> Sergeant <hi>Gerrard</hi> Atturny Generall; <hi>Carre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> of the <hi>Dutch: Plowdon</hi> the learnedſt man of that age, in the knowledge of the Law, and Cuſtomes of the Realm.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Law in all ages without any controverſie is and hath beene: That <hi>no Act of Parliament bindes the Subjects of this Land without the aſſent of the King, either for perſon, Lands, Goods, or Fame.</hi> No man can ſhew any ſillable, letter, or line to the contrary in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33168:4"/>the bookes of the Law, or printed Acts of Parliament, in any age in this Land. If the vertuall Power be in the Houſes, there needes no aſſent of the Kings. The ſtiles of the Acts printed from 9. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. to 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. were either,
<note place="margin">9 Hen. 3. <hi>Magna Charta. So in every age till this day, and in every Kings time, as appears by the Acts in Print.</hi> 1 <hi>part of the Inſtit Sect.</hi> 234. <hi>in fine, where many of the Law-Bookes are cited.</hi> 7. H. 7.14.12. <hi>of</hi> Hen. 7.20.</note> 
                     <hi>The King ordaines at his Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. or the King ordaineth by the advice of his Prelats and Barons, and at the humble Petition of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, &amp;c. In <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. his time the Stile altered, and hath ſithence continued thus, It is ordained by the Kings Majeſty, and the Lords ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and temporall, and Commons in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled. So that alwayes the Aſſent of the King giveth the life to all, as the ſoule to the body; and therefore our Law-Bookes call the King the Fountaine of Juſtice, and the life of the Law.</p>
                  <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">2. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22. 4 <hi>pars inſtit.</hi> 42. <hi>M. Prin in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the great Seale Fol.</hi> 17.27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.</note> Mercy as well as Juſtice belongs by the law of the Land only to the King. This is confeſſed by Maſter <hi>Prynn,</hi> and it is ſo without any quection: The King can only pardon, and never more cauſe to have ſufficient pardons then in ſuch trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome times as theſe, and God ſend us pardons and peace. None can give any pardon, but the King by the Law of the Land: <hi>The whole and ſole power of pardoning Treaſons and Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies belongs to the King,</hi> are the words of the Law, and it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to take it from any other and utterly invalid. 27 Hen. 8. Cap 24.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſummoned her firſt Parliament, to be held the 23. of January, in the firſt yeare of Her Majeſties Raigne. The Lords and Commons aſſembled by force of the ſame writ the 23. day the Queen fell ſick and could not appeare in her perſon in Parliament that day, and therefore proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued it untill the 25. of the ſame Month of January. <hi>Reſolved by all the Judges of</hi> England,
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Of Eliz. Dier.</hi> 203.</note> 
                     <hi>that the Parliament began not the day of the returne of the writ, viz. the</hi> 23. <hi>of January, when the Lords and Commons appeared, but the</hi> 25. <hi>of the ſaid moneth when the Queen came in perſon:</hi> Which ſheweth evidently that this virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſence is a meere deluding fiction that hath no ground in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33168:5"/>Law, reaſon, or ſenſe. They have the King now a priſoner at <hi>Holmby,</hi> with guards upon him, and yet they governe by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Power of their Priſoner. Theſe are ſome of the cauſes and reaſons which moved me to deliver that paper to Maſter <hi>Corbet,</hi> which I am ready to juſtifie with my life, and ſhould hold it a great honour to die for the honourable and holy Lawes of the Land.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <p>That which will ſave this Land from deſtruction, is an Act of Oblivion, and His Majeſties gracious generall pardon, the Souldiers their Arears, and every man his owne, and Truth and Peace eſtabliſhed in the Land, and a favourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the ſatisfaction of tender Conſciences.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Aprill</hi> 29. 1647.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>David Jenkins.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE ARMIES INDEMNITY, With Addition; <hi>Together,</hi> With a Declaration, ſhewing how eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Subject of <hi>England</hi> ought to be tried for Treaſons, Felonies, and all other Capitall Crimes, as it is ſet down in the Lawes of the LAND.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>David Jenkins,</hi> now Priſoner in the Tower of LONDON.</p>
                  <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:6"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33168:6"/>
                  <head>The Armies Indemnity, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>UPon the publiſhing of the Ordinance of the 22. of May laſt, for the Indemnity of the Army, certain Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen well affected to the peace of the Kingdome, and ſafety of the Army, deſired me to ſet downe in writing, whether by the Law of the Land, the ſaid Ordinance did ſecure them from danger, as to the matters therein menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. For whoſe ſatisfaction in a buſineſſe wherein the lives and fortunes of ſo many men were concerned, and the Peace of the Kingdome involved, I conceived I was bound in duty and conſcience, faithfully and truly to ſet downe what the Law of the Land therein is, which accordingly I have with all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity expreſſed in this following diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>The danger of the Army by the Law of the Land is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to all men.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. 2 <hi>Ri.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. 1 <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>Phil. and Mary. c.</hi> 10</note> It is high Treaſon by the Law of the Land to leavy warre againſt the King, to compaſſe or imagine his death, or the death of his Queene, or of his eldeſt Sonne, to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit his Money, or his great Seale; They are the words of the Law. Other Treaſons then are ſpecified in that Act, are declared to be no Treaſons untill the King and his Parliament ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare otherwiſe, they are the very words of the Law.
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Pars inſtit. Pag.</hi> 22. &amp; 2. <hi>pars inſtit. Pag.</hi> 47, 48. &amp; 4. <hi>pars inſtit.</hi> P. 23.48.29.</note> King and Commons, King and Lords, Commons and Lords, cannot declare any other thing to be Treaſon, then there is declared: as appeares by the Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> in the places cited in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin: A Law-booke publiſhed by order of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons this Parliament,
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Pars inſtit. cap.</hi> Treaſon <hi>Pa.</hi> 9, 10, &amp; 12. Mr <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the Sollicitor in his Speech up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the araign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Earle of <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Printed by order of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. <hi>p.</hi> 7. 13.</note> as appeares in the laſt leafe of the ſecond part of the Inſtitutes, publiſhed likewiſe by their Order.</p>
                  <p>The Reſolutions of all the Judges of England, upon the ſaid Statute of the 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. (as appeares in the ſaid third part of the Inſtitutes, <hi>Chap.</hi> High-Treaſon) have been, that to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the King untill he agree to certaine demands is High-Treaſon;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33168:7"/>to ſeize his Ports, Forts, Magazine for Warre, are High-Treaſon: to alter the Lawes is High-Treaſon.</p>
                  <p>The word King in the Statute of 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Kings naturall perſon: for that perſon can only dye, have a wife, have a ſonne, or be impriſoned.</p>
                  <p>The Privilege of Parliament protects no man from treaſon or felony,
<note place="margin">4. <hi>Pars inſtit. c. Parl. p.</hi> 25.</note> howbeit he be a Member: much leſſe can they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect others. Thoſe who cannot protect themſelves, have no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to make Ordinances to protect others who are no Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
                  <p>The Statute of 11.
<note place="margin">11. M. 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. doth by expreſſe words free all perſons who adhere to the King.</p>
                  <p>The Army by an Act of Indemnity free themſelves from all thoſe dangers,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stamford. l.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 99. 18 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes at large 144. 20 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 11. <hi>Rie.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. 4 <hi>Pars inſtit. Pag.</hi> 23.48.29.</note> which an Ordinance can no more doe then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale all the Lawes of the Land, the whole and ſole power by Law to pardon all Treaſons, Felonies, &amp;c. being ſolely and wholly in the King, as is cleared by the Statute of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 24. and the Law of the Land in all times.</p>
                  <p>Having ſhewed the danger of the Army by the Law of the Land, next conſider the Ordinance of the Lords and Commons publiſhed the 22. of May laſt for their Indemnity. By the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing diſcourſe it doth appeare they have no Indemnity at all thereby.</p>
                  <p>The Indemnity propoſed by the Ordinance, is for any Act done by the authority of the Parl. or for the ſervice or bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereof: and that the Judges and all other Miniſters of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhall allow thereof.</p>
                  <p>This Ordinance cannot ſecure the Army for theſe reaſons:</p>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>Their Judges are ſworne to doe juſtice according to the Law of the Land,
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Pars inſtit. Pag.</hi> 22. 2 <hi>Pars inſtit.</hi> 47, 48. 1. <hi>Pars inſtit.</hi> 193. Princes <hi>caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>perte.</hi>
                        </note> and therefore the Judges muſt be forſworne men, if they obey it: becauſe an Ordinance of both Houſes is no Law of the Land; and no man can beleeve they will perjure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo palpably and viſibly in the eye of the world.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33168:7"/>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>All trials for Treaſons, Felonies, Robberies,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Magna Charta cap.</hi> 29. 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap</hi> 4. 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. 37. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> and ſuch like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall offences, are by the Law of the Land to be by indictment of a Jury appointed out of the Neighbourhood where the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was done. There is no common Jury-man but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands what the Law is in theſe caſes as well as the beſt Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers: and the Law makes the Jury Judges of the fact, whereby the ſouldier is left to their mercy whom he hath offended (as ſome of them have lately had wofull experience,
<note place="margin">Declaration of the Army pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Officers ſubſcribed.</note> and thereupon doe rightly apprehend their danger) Now no man can thinke that the Jurors will perjure themſelves to acquit the ſouldiers for robbing and plundring of the Countries, and thereby ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroy their owne Rights and Properties.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>If the Judges conceive (as they may) that the taking of other mens horſes or goods, is not by the Authority of Parliament, or for the ſervice and benefit thereof, the ſouldier dyes for it: they may ſay to ſteale or rob any man of his goods is not for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ſervice but againſt it, which was alwayes the ſence of the people, and doubtleſſe the Jurors will not thinke otherwiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <p>This Ordinance is reſtrained to the authority,
<note place="margin">4. <hi>Pars inſtit. pag.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Pars inſtit. pag.</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Pars inſtit. pag.</hi> 1. 28. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l</hi> 11. <hi>Dier</hi> 38. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ſol.</hi> 60. 12. <hi>H.</hi> 7.20. 1. <hi>Pars inſtit.</hi> 159. <hi>Princes</hi> caſe 8. reports.</note> ſervice or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Parliament. The Lords and Commons make no more a Parliament by the Law of the Land then a body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a head makes a man: for a Parliament is a body compoſed of a King their head; the Lords and Commons the Members. All three together make one body, and that is the Parliament, and none other. And the Judges may, ought, and I beleeve will according to their Oathes proceed as not bound at all by this Ordinance. For it is reſtrained to the Authority of Parliament, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>vice or benefit thereof, whereas the two Houſes are not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>liament, but only parts thereof, and by the abuſe and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33168:8"/>of this word <hi>Parliament,</hi> they have miſerably deceived the people.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <p>This Ordinance is againſt their Ordinances which expreſly prohibit plundring,
<note place="margin">28 <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. Col. of Ord. firſt part. 565.592.605. ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> and ſo there is one Ordinance againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereby their Judges have an out-let to proceed on the one or the other, and thereby the Army hath no manner of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>The word Parliament is a French word (howbeit ſuch Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies were before the Norman Conqueſt here) &amp; ſignifies in that Language to conſult &amp; treat:
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pars iaſtit.</hi> 109. 1 <hi>Pars inſtit.</hi> 110. 4 <hi>Pars p.</hi> 49.</note> that is the ſenſe of the word <hi>Parler</hi> in the French Tongue. The Writ whereby the two Houſes are aſſembled, which is called the Writ of Summons of Parliament, at all times, and at this Parliament uſed, and which is the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ground and foundation of their meeting, is for the Lords of the Houſe of Peeres, the Judges and Kings Councell to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult and treate with the King (that is the <hi>Parler</hi>) of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, touching 1. the King, ſecondly, the defence of his Kingdome, thirdly, the defence of the Church of England. It cannot be a Parliament that will not Parle with their King, but keep him in priſon, and not ſuffer him to come to them and parle; and therefore the Law, and ſence, and reaſon, informing every man that is no manner of Parliament (the King with whom they ſhould parle, being ſo reſtrained that they will not parle with him) The Army hath no manner of ſecurity by this Ordinance: For their indemnification referres to that which is not in being untill the King be at liberty.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <p>It is more then probable that their Judges before the laſt circuite had inſtructions to the effect or this Ordinance: <note place="margin">The Common Souldiers ſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Apology. 6. Grievances of the Army publiſhed 15. <hi>May</hi> laſt. Three grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of Col. <hi>Riche's</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>but they the Judges making conſcience of their Oath, laid aſide the ſaid Inſtructions, and ought, and may, and it is beleeved will no more regard this Ordinance, then the ſaid inſtructions: What was done in the laſt circuite, the Army well knowes, touching many of their fellow-ſouldiers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33168:8"/>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>The Houſes in their firſt Propoſition to his Majeſty for a ſafe and well-grounded peace, ſent to Neweaſtle to deſire a pardon from his Majeſty for themſelves: they who deſire a pardon, cannot grant a pardon (common reaſon dictates this to every man) and therefore that the Army ſhould accept an Indemnity from them, who ſeeke it for themſelves, or ſhould conceive it of any manner of force, is a fancy: ſo that no man in the whole Army but may apprehend, that it is vaine and a meere deluſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>His Majeſty by his gracious Meſſage of the 12. of <hi>May</hi> faſt, the 22 of the ſame, hath offered an Act of Oblivion, and a generall pardon to all his people, this done the Law doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnifie the Army (without all manner of ſcruple) for any thing that hath beene done: for it is an Act of Parliament when the King and two Houſes concurre, and bindes all men. There is no ſafety by the Ordinance; There is ſafety by an act of Parliament: And will not reaſonable men preferre that which is ſafe before that which is unſafe?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <p>His Majeſty by his ſaid Letter agrees to pay the Arreares of the Army; I am ſure that it is a publique Debt, and the chiefeſt and the firſt that by the two Houſes ſhould be paid, and before any Divident or Gratuities beſtowed among themſelves; for their Bloud, Limbes, and Lives have put and kept the both Houſes at reſt in the power they have: So by this concurrence of his Majeſty for your indemnity, and for your Arreares, The Army have not an Ordinance, or the Publique Faith, but the Law of the Land to make ſure unto them their Indemnity for all Acts, and for their Arreares, and therewith alſo bring peace to the Land.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33168:9"/>
                     <head>XI.</head>
                     <p>The Kingdome and people generally deſire theſe things. To ſuch an Army, juſt and reaſonable things muſt not be denyed; the things formerly propoſed are moſt juſt and reaſonable, you may have them if you will; if you will not, you render this Kingdome miſerable;
<note place="margin">Mr <hi>Pyms</hi> Speech againſt the Earle of <hi>Strafford. p.</hi> 16 Sixt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Printed by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> wherein you will have your ſhares of miſeries: The head and the body are ſuch an incorporation as cannot be diſſolved without the deſtruction of both.</p>
                     <p>The Additional Ordinance of both houſes paſſed the fifth of <hi>June</hi> inſtant for the fuller indemnity of the Army, makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to the matter. 1. For that it extends not to Felony, Homicide, Burglary, Robbery, or any other capitall crime, which is the maine buſineſſe inſiſted upon, and moſt concerneth the Souldiers ſecurity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>The both Houſes in the ſaid Additionall Ordinance, ſay, that it is expedient that all offences be pardoned and put in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion. Pardon and Oblivion cannot bee underſtood to bee for a time, but for ever: and they themſelves confeſſe, that an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is not binding but <hi>pro tempore</hi> which with the moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Interpretation can be but a reprieve or delay of the execution of the Law, and therefore that cannot pardon or put in oblivion by their owne ſhewing.</p>
                     <p>But the Law of the Land is,
<note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> (and ſo it hath conſtantly been practiſed in all times) that no perſons of what eſtate ſoever, have any power to pardon Treaſon, Felony, or any other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but the King onely, who hath the ſole and whole power to pardon all ſuch crimes whatſoever. And in the ſame manner an Ordinance is of no Authority at all to take away the right of private mens actions, by any evidence it can give: In truth all the evidence that this Ordinance will give is, that it records to poſterity nothing but a lawleſſe and diſtempered time.</p>
                     <p>For remedy therefore I ſay againe, it is a certaine truth, This Kingdome without an act of Oblivion, and a generall Pardon,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33168:9"/>and the payment of Souldiers arreares, and a meet regard had to tender Conſciences, will unavoidably be ruined.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>June 10. 1647.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>David Jenkins,</hi> Priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Sundry Acts of Parliament mentioned and cited in the Armies Indemnities: ſet forth in words at large for the better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of ſuch as deſire to be rightly informed.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>25. Edw. 3.</hi> Chap. <hi>2.</hi> A Declaration what offences ſhall be adjudged Treaſon.</head>
                     <p>VVHereas divers opinions have been before this time, in what caſe Treaſon ſhall be ſaid, &amp; in what not: The K. at the requeſt of the Lords and of the Commons hath made a Declaration in the manner as hereafter followeth: That is to ſay, When a man doth compaſſe, or imagine the death of our Lord the King, or of our Lady the Queen, or of their eldeſt Son and Heire: or if a man do violate the Kings companion, or the Kings eldeſt daughter unmarried, or the wife of the Kings el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſonne and heire: or if a man do levie war againſt the Lord our King in his Realme, or bee adherent to the Kings enemies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33168:10"/>in his Realm, giving to them aid and comfort in the Realme, or elſe-where, and thereof be probably attainted of open deed by people of their condition; And if a man counterfeit the Kings great or privie Scale, or his Money: and if a man bring falſe money into this Realm, counterfeit to the money of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the money called <hi>Lusburgh,</hi> or other like to the ſaid money of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>11. Hen. 7.</hi> Cap. <hi>1.</hi> None that ſhall attend upon the King, and doe him true ſervice, ſhall bee attainted or forfeit any thing.</head>
                     <p>THe King our Soveraign Lord calling to his remembrance the duty of allegiance of his Subjects of this his Realm, and that they by reaſon of the ſame are bound to ſerve their Prince and Soveraign Lord for the time being in his wars, for the defence of Him and the Land, againſt every rebellion pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and might raiſed, reared againſt him, and with him to enter and abide in ſervice in battell, if caſe ſo require, and that for the ſame ſervice what fortune ever fall by chance in the ſame bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell againſt the minde and will of the Prince (as in this Land ſometime paſſed hath been ſeen) that it is not reaſonable, but againſt all lawes, reaſon and good conſcience, that the ſaid Subjects going with their Soveraigne Lord in wars, attending upon him in his perſon, or being in other places by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement within this Land or without any thing ſhould loſe or forfeit, for doing their duty or ſervice of Allegiance. It be therefore ordained, enacted, and eſtabliſhed by the King our Soveraigne Lord, by the advice and aſſent of the Lords ſpiritual and temporall, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by authority of the ſame, that from henceforth no manner of perſon or perſons whatſoever he or they be, that attend upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the King and Soveraigne Lord of this Land for the time being, in his perſon, and doe him true and faithfull ſervice of allegiance in the ſame, or be in other places by his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in his wars, within this Land or without, that for the ſaid deed and true duty of allegiance he or they be in no wiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33168:10"/>convict or attaint of high treaſon, nor of other offences for that cauſe, by act of Parliament, or otherwiſe by any proceſſe of Law, whereby hee or any of them ſhall loſe or forfeit life, lands, tenements, rents, poſſeſſions, hereditaments, goods, chattels, or any other things, but to be for that deed and ſervice utterly diſcharged of any vexation, trouble, or loſſe. And if any act or acts, or other proceſſe of the Law hereafter thereupon for the ſame, happen to be made contrary to this Ordinance, that then that act or acts, or other proceſſe of the Law, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they ſhall be, ſtand and be utterly void. Provided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, that no perſon or perſons ſhall take any benefit or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by this Act, which ſhall hereafter decline from his or their ſaid allegiance.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 24. In the Statute of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. It is enacted, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons of what eſtate or degree ſoever they be of, ſhall have any power or authority to pardon or remit any treaſon, murders, man-ſlaughters, or any kinde of Fellonies, &amp;c. but that the King ſhall have the ſole and whole power and authority thereof united and knit to the Imperiall Crowne, as of right it appertaineth, &amp;c. And in the ſame it is enacted further, that none ſhall have power, of what eſtate, degree, or condition ſoever they be, to make Juſtices of Eyre, Juſtices of Aſſize, Juſtices of the Peace, &amp;c. but all ſuch officers and Miniſters ſhall be made by Letters Patents under the Kings great Seale in the name and by the authority of the King and his Heires and Succeſſors Kings of this Realme.</p>
                     <p>In the firſt yeare of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and the firſt Chapter, It is enacted by the Queen, with the conſent of the Lords and Commons, That no deed, or offence, by Act of Parliament made treaſon, ſhall be taken, deemed, or adjudged to be high treaſon, but only ſuch as be declared and expreſſed to be treaſon by the Act of Parliament, made 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. before mentioned.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33168:11"/>
                  <head>A Declaration of M. <hi>David Ienkins,</hi> now Priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> one of His Majeſties Iudges in <hi>Wales,</hi> for tryalls of Treaſons, Murthers, Felonies, and all other capitall crimes, that they ought only to be by Iuries and not otherwiſe, unleſſe it be by Act of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>THe common Law of this Land is, That every free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is ſubject to a tryall by bill of Attainder in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, wherein His Majeſty and both Houſes muſt neceſſarily concurre, for that tryall and attainder is an Act of Parliament to which all men are ſubject to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mag. Chart. cap.</hi> 29. 2 <hi>part. inſtit. fol.</hi> 28 29.46.48, 49, 50. compoſed by Sir <hi>Ed. Cooke</hi> and publiſhed by the Order of the Houſe of Commons in <hi>May</hi> 1641.</note> No man ſhall otherwiſe be deſtroyed, &amp;c but by the lawfull judgement of his Peers, or by the common Law of the Land. Peers to Noblemen are Noblemen, Peers to the Commons are Knights, Gentlemen, &amp;c. Judgement of Peers refers to Peers, thoſe words, <hi>The Law of the Land,</hi> refers to the Commons, the Law of the Land is for the tryall of the life of a free Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by Indictment, Preſentment of good and lawfull men where the deed is done, or by Writ originall of the common Law, all this is declared in <hi>Magna Charta</hi> c. 29. and by 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. c. 4. 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. c. 3. 37. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. c. 8. 42. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. c. 3. If the Lords will try any man by an Ordinance, they deſtroy that excellent Act of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and all thoſe other good Lawes.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Simon de Bereford</hi> a free Commoner of <hi>England</hi> was condemned by the Lords to death by an Ordinance, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lords better conſidering the matter, that they might be acquitted of that ſentence; became ſuters to the King, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33168:11"/>what they had ſo done in future time might not be drawn into preſident, becauſe that which they had ſo done was againſt the Law,
<note n="b" place="margin">Rot. Par. 1. roule 4. E. 3. Num. 2. part inſt page 50. with this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. grees Sir <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n Lees</hi> caſe, Rot. Par. 42. E. 3. Num. 22.23. 2. inſt. fol. 50.</note> with this agrees the practice and uſage of all times in this Land, all the free Commoners of this Kingdome have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes been tryed and acquitted or condemned in capitall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by Jurers of their equalls.</p>
                  <p>An Ordinance bindeth not in Law at all,
<note n="c" place="margin">See 4. part. inſt. fol. 23.48.292. 2. part. inſt. f. 47, 48.</note> and but <hi>pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> as the two Houſes now affirme, a mans life cannot be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that which is not binding, and to continue for all times, for a life loſt cannot be reſtored.</p>
                  <p>By an Act of Parliament of the 1. and 2. of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> chap. 10. It is enacted that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> tryalls for Treaſon hereafter to be had, ſhall be according to the courſe of the common-law.</p>
                  <p>If the crime charged upon any be treaſon againſt the two Houſes (againſt the Parliament it cannot be, for there is no Parliament without the King) that is no Treaſon in Law, as appeares by 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>cha.</hi> 10. 1. <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>Philip and Mary, chap.</hi> 10. 3 <hi>part. of the inſtitutes Page</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>An Act of Parliament to make any a Judge where he is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is a void act,
<note n="d" place="margin">Dr <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ams</hi> caſe 8. part of <hi>Cooks</hi> reports.</note> for none can be a Judge and party in the ſame cauſe, and therefore the Houſe of Peers being a party touching the crime charged upon any man, whom they would try by an Ordinance for Treaſon againſt both Houſes, cannot be a Judge.</p>
                  <p>By the Petition of Right,
<note n="e" place="margin">Petition of Right. 3. <hi>Car. Regis.</hi>
                     </note> if any man deſerve death he ought to ſuffer the ſame according to the Lawes of the Land eſtabliſhed, and not otherwiſe; but an Ordinance of the Lords is no eſtabliſhed law.</p>
                  <p>The Proteſtation, the Vow and Covenant, the ſolemne League and Covenant, the Declarations of both Houſes, had, made and publiſhed ſithence this unnaturall Warre, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things ſworne and ſet downe to be for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Lawes, the people of this land ought to enjoy the benefit of their Birth-right the Law of the Land, and the making good of the ſaid Proteſtation, Vow and Covenant, League and Covenant, and Declarations, otherwiſe truth muſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33168:12"/>be ſaid and will be ſaid, that there is brought in a new arbitrary and tyrannicall government.</p>
                  <p>If the Lords have taken one mans life by an Ordinance, they are not bound to take any more, and the caſe differs in caſe any appeale be made from a tryall by Ordinance to a tryall at common law, which was not done by that man whoſe life was taken away by an Ordinance.</p>
                  <p>The Lords ought to remember, that his Majeſty and his Progenitors have made them a houſe of Peeres, they are truſted to counſell him in peace,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nevels</hi> caſe 8. part <hi>Cooks</hi> reports.</note> and defend him in war, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty in Parliament is to conſult and treat with the Peers, and with his Counſell at Law, Judges, his Sergeants, Atturney, and Solicitor, and Maſters of the Chancery, the Lords and that counſell by the reſpective Writs of Summons to Parliament are to give Counſell,
<note n="g" place="margin">4 <hi>Pars inſtit. fol.</hi> 4.9.</note> the Houſe of Commons by their Writ to performe and conſent.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe of Lords, the Court of Parliament only is, for they only examine upon oath,
<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 20.</note> with them, the King in perſon ſits, and by them there erroneous judgements
<note n="*" place="margin">14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> (upon a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Majeſty for obtaining of a Writ of Errour) by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Judges are reverſed, or affirmed, &amp;c. the Lords are to remember that their eminency and grandeur, is preſerved by the Laws, if they leave all to will, and diſhonour their King, and make nothing of the Lawes, they will make nothing of themſelves in the end.</p>
                  <p>And therefore, it is well worth your obſervation what was ſaid by Mr <hi>Iohn Pym</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Commons in his ſpeech againſt the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> in the beginning of the Parliament, which ſpeech is publiſhed by the expreſſe order of the Houſe of Commons, the words are theſe. <hi>The Law is that which puts a difference betwixt good and evill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt juſt and unjuſt, if you take away the Law, all things will fall into a confuſion, every man will become a Law unto himſelfe, which in the depraved condition of humane nature muſt needs produce many great enormities: Luſt will become a Law, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy will become a Law, Covetouſneſſe and Ambition will become Lawes, and what di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tates, what deciſions ſuch Lawes will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, may eaſily be diſcerned,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">i See part. book deel. pag. 140.163.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They that love this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33168:12"/>as things now ſtand, will uſe all meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure an Act of Oblivion, a generall pardon from his Majeſty, the Souldiers their Arrears, and tender conſciences a juſt and reaſonable ſatisfaction, elſe we all muſt periſh, firſt or laſt.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <hi>God preſerve His Majeſty, and the Lawes wherein their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and the whole Kingdome are concerned.</hi>
                     <date>Mai. 17. 1647.</date>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>David Ienkins</hi> Priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:13"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33168:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>TO THE HONORABLE Societies of <hi>Grayes-Jnne,</hi> and of the reſt of the Innes of Court, and to all the Profeſſors of the LAW.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Have now ſpent Forty five yeares in the Study of the Lawes of this Land being my profeſſion, under and by the conduct of which Lawes this common-wealth hath flouriſhed for ſome ages paſt in great ſplendor and happineſſe <hi>(jam ſeges eſt ubi Troja fuit)</hi> The great &amp; full body of this Kingdome hath of late yeares fallen into an extreame ſickneſſe it is truly ſaid that the cauſe of the diſeaſe being knowne, the diſeaſe is eaſily cured. There is none of you I hope, but doth heartily wiſh the recovery of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon parent, our native country <hi>(Moribus antiquis ſtat res Britannica)</hi> I call God to witnes that this diſcourſe of mine hath no other end then my wiſhes of the common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od: how farr I have been from Ambition, my life paſt, and your owne knowledge of me, can abundantly informe you, and many of you well know, that I ever d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teſted the ſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and monopolies, &amp; that in the beginning of this Parliament, for oppoſing the exceſſes of one of the Biſhopes, I lay under three Excommunications and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of ſeeventy ſeven Articles in the high Commiſſion Court. His ſacred Majeſty: (God is my witnes) made mee a judge in the parts of Wales againſt my will, and all the meanes I was able to make; and a patent for my place was ſent mee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33168:14"/>for the which I have not paid one farthing, and the place is of ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable a benefit that it is worth but <hi>80. <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> when paid, and it coſt me every yeare I ſerved twice as much out of mine owne eſtate in the way of an ordinary and frugall expence. That which gave me comfort was that I knew well that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie was a juſt and a prudent Prince.</p>
                  <p>In the time of the Attournyſhips of Maſter <hi>Noy</hi> and the Lord <hi>Banks,</hi> they Were pleaſed to make often uſe of me, and many refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences concerning ſuits at Court upon that occaſion came to my knowledge, and as I ſhall anſwer to God upon my laſt account this is truth, that all or moſt of the referrences which I have ſeen in that Kind (and I have ſeen many) were to this effect, That his Majeſty would be informed by his Counſell if the ſuits preferred were agreeable to the Lawes, and not inconvenient to his people, before he would paſs them. [What could a juſt and pious Prince do more?] Gentlemen you ſhall find the Cauſe and the Curſe of the preſent great diſtemper in this diſcourſe, and God Proſper it in your hands, thoughts, and words, as the Caſe deſerves.</p>
                  <p>Hold to the Lawes, this great body recovers: for ſake them, it will certainly periſh. I have reſolved to tender my ſelfe a Sacrifice for them as cheerefully, and I hope (by Gods aſſiſtance) as conſtantly as old <hi>Eleazer</hi> did for the holy Lawes of his Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your well-wiſher
DAVID JENKINS. Now Priſoner in the Tower.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33168:14"/>
                  <head>LEX TERRAE.</head>
                  <p>THE Law of this Land hath three grounds. Firſt <hi>Cuſtom.</hi> Secondly <hi>Iudiciall Records.</hi> Thirdly <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The two latter are but declarations of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law</hi> and <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of the Realme, touching <hi>Royall Government.</hi> And this Law of <hi>Royall-Government,</hi> is a <hi>Law-Fundamentall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Government of this Kingdome by a <hi>Royall Soveraign,</hi> hath beene as ancient as hiſtory is, or the memoriall of any time;
<note place="margin">The kings prerogative is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall part of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law. <hi>Com: Litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 344:</note> what power this <hi>Soveraignty</hi> alwayes had and uſed in warre and peace in this land, is the ſcope of this diſcourſe; That <hi>Vſage</hi> ſo practiſed makes therein a <hi>Fundamentall Law,</hi> and the <hi>Common. Law</hi> of the Land is common <hi>Vſage, Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wdens Commentaries.</hi> 195.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt of our Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ithence the Norman conqueſt, the firſt <hi>William,</hi> ſecond <hi>William, Henry</hi> the firſt, <hi>Stephen, Henry</hi> the ſecond and <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, the Cuſtoms of the Realme touching <hi>Royall Government,</hi> were never queſtioned: The ſaid Kings injoyed them in a full meaſunt. In King <hi>Iohns</hi> time the Nobles and Commons of the Realme conceiving that the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cuſtomes and Rights were violated, and thereupon preſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid King to allow them in the ſeventeenth of King <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſaid Liberties were by King <hi>Iohn</hi> allowed, and by his ſon <hi>Hen.</hi> the third, after in the ninth yeere of his Reigne confirmed, and are called <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and <hi>Charta de Foreſta</hi> declared foure hundred twenty two yeeres ſithhence by the ſaid Charters.</p>
                  <p>Now reſts to be conſidered, after the Subjects had obtained their Rights and Liberties, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no other then their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cuſtomes (and the fundamentall Rights of the King as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne</hi> are no other.) How the Rights of <hi>Soveraignty</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in practiſe from <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds time untill this preſent Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ament of the third of November 1640. for before <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds time, the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> had a very full Power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex habet Poteſtatem &amp; juriſdictionem ſuper omnes qui in Regnoſuo ſunt, ea quae ſunt juriſdictionis &amp; Pacis ad nullum
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33168:15"/>pertinent niſi ad Regiam dignitatem,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>reacton temps. H.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Sect</hi> 1</note> habet etiam coeroionem, ut Delinquentes puniat &amp; coerceat;</hi> This proves where the ſupreame Power is.</p>
                  <p>A Delinquent is hee who adheres to the Kings Enemies <hi>Com Sur. Littl.</hi> 261. This ſhewes who are Delinquents.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Omnis ſub Rege, &amp; ipſe ſub nullo niſi tuntum Deo, non eſt inferior ſibi Subjectis,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sect</hi> 5 <hi>Bractabid.</hi>
                        </note> non parem habet in Regnoſuo.</hi> This ſhewes where the ſupreame power is.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex non habet ſuperiorem niſi Deum, ſatis habet ad poenam quod Deum expectat ultorem.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bracton lib.</hi> 5. <hi>tract</hi> 3. <hi>de de ſaltis Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Bracton. Lib</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7.</note> This ſhewes where the ſuprerme power i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Treaſons, Fellonies, and other Pleas of the Crowne, are <hi>propri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cauſa Regis.</hi> This ſhewes the ſame power.</p>
                  <p>By theſe paſſages it doth appeare what the Cuſtome was for the power of <hi>Soveraignty</hi> before that time; the power of the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, of coyning of Money, of making Leagues with forreigne Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the power of Pardoning, of making of Officers, &amp;c. All Kings had them, the ſaid Powers have no beginning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sexto Ed:</hi> 1. <hi>Comſur. Littl.</hi> 85. Liege Homage, every Subject owes to the King <hi>(viz)</hi> Faith <hi>de Membre,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ewd.</hi> 1.</note> de vita, de terren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore,</hi> the forme of the Oath <hi>inter vetera ſtatuta</hi> is ſet down; We read of no ſuch, or any Homage made to the two Houſes but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of ſuch made by them.</p>
                  <p>It is declared by the Prelates, Earles, Barrons, and Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Realm, that it belongeth to the King and his Royall Segniory,
<note place="margin">7. Ed. 1. <hi>statuts at large<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>l.</hi> 42.</note> ſtraitly to defend force of Armour, and all other force againſt the Kings peace, at all times when it ſhall pleaſe him, and to puniſh them that ſhall doe contrary according to the Law and Uſage of the Realme, and hereunto they are bound to ayde their Soveraigne Lord, at all ſeaſons when need ſhall be. Here the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power in the time of Parliament, by both Houſes is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to belong to the King.</p>
                  <p>At the beginning of every Parliament, all Armes are, or ought to be forbidden to be born in London,
<note place="margin">7. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.4. <hi>pars inſtit.</hi> 14. 1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>de Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus.</hi>
                     </note> Weſtminſter, or the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs. This condemnes the multitudes comming to Weſtminſter, and the Guards of armed men.</p>
                  <p>All who held by Knights-ſervice, and had twenty pounds <hi>per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> were diſtraynable <hi>ad Arma militaria ſuſcipienda.</hi> This
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33168:15"/>agrees with the Records of ancient time, continued cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ntly in all Kings times, but at this Parliament 3. November 1640. The King, out of his grace, diſcharged this duty, which proves that the power of warre and preparation thereto, belongs not to the two houſes, but only to the King.</p>
                  <p>The two <hi>Spencers</hi> in <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ed</hi> 3. <hi>Calvins Caſe Cook l.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 1</note> time hatched (to cover their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) this damnable and damned opinion <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Ligeance was more by reaſon of the Kings politique capacity then of his perſon, upon which they inferred theſe execrable and deteſtable conſequences. Firſt, if the King demeaned not himſelfe by reaſon in the right of his Crown, his Lieges are bound by Oath to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him. Secondly, ſeeing the King could not be removed by ſuit of Law it was to be done by force. Thirdly, that his Lieges be bound to govern in default of him.</p>
                  <p>All which tenets were condemned by two Parliaments, the one called <hi>exilium Hugonis</hi> in <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. time; the other by 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. All which Articles againſt the <hi>Spencers</hi> are confirmed by this laſt Statute, the Articles are extant in the booke called <hi>vetera Statuta.</hi> The ſeparation of the Kings perſon from his power, is the principall Article condemned, and yet all theſe three damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, deteſtable, and execrable conſequents, are the grounds where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this preſent time relies, and the principles whereupon the two Houſes found their Cauſe,</p>
                  <p>The Villeine of a Lord, in the preſence of the King;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Plowdon com.</hi> 322, 27. <hi>aſſ. pl.</hi> 49. 33 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ayde der<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y</hi> 103 <hi>Fitz.</hi> 10 <hi>H.</hi> 7 16.</note> cannot be ſeized for the preſence of the King is a protection for that time to him: This ſhewes what reverence the Law gives to the perſon of a King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reges, ſacro oleo uncti ſunt capaces ſpirituallis juriſdictionis</hi> But the two Houſes were never held capable of that power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex eſt perſona mixta cum ſacerdote, habet Eccleſiaſticam &amp; ſpititualem juriſdictionem.</hi> This ſhewes the Kings power in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Canſes.</p>
                  <p>The lands of the King is caled in Law <hi>Patromonium ſacrum.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Com. Sur Littl Sect</hi> 4. 3. Ed. 3. 19</note> The houſes ſhould not have meddled with that ſacred Patr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>y.</p>
                  <p>The King hath no Peere in his land, and cannot be judged? <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> the two Houſes are not above him.</p>
                  <p>The Parliament 15. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3 was repealed, for that it was againſt the Kings Lawes and prerogative. 4 <hi>pars. inſtit fol.</hi> 52. this ſhewes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33168:16"/>cleerely the propoſitions ſent to Newcaſtle, ought not to have been preſented to his Majeſty, for that they are contrary to the Lawes and his Prerogative.</p>
                  <p>The Lords and Commons cannot aſſent in Parliament to any thing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ends to the diſinheriſion of the King and his Crowne,
<note place="margin">4 <hi>pars Cookes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. fol.</hi> 14 42. <hi>E.</hi> 3. Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment Rol. num. 7. <hi>Lex &amp; conſuetudo Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti.</hi>
                     </note> to which they are ſworn. This condemnes the ſaid Propoſitions likewiſe.</p>
                  <p>To depoſe the King, to impriſon him untill he aſſent to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine demands, A war to alter the Religion eſtabliſhed by Law, or any other Law, or to remove Councellors, to hold a Caſtle or Fort againſt the King; are offences againſt that Law declared to be treaſon by the reſolutions herein after mentioned, by that Law men are bound to ayd the King when war is levied againſt him in his Realme.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> King, in this Statute muſt be intended in his naturall body and perſon that only can die; for to compaſs his death, and declare it by overt Act is declared thereby treaſon, to incounter in fight ſuch as come to ayd the King in his wars, is treaſon.</p>
                  <p>Compaſſing of the Queenes death, of the Kings eldeſt ſon, to coyne his money, to counterfeit his Great-Seale, to levie Warre againſt him, to adhere to ſuch as ſhall ſo do, are declared by that Act to be high Treaſon. This Statute cannot refer to the King in his politique capacity, but to his naturall, which is inſeperable from the politique, for a body politique can have neither. Wife nor Child,
<note place="margin">21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.14.</note> not, levie Warre, nor do any Act but by the operation of the naturall body: A Corporation or body politique hath no ſoule or life, but is a fiction of the Law, and the Statute meant not fictitious perſons, but the body naturall, conjoyned with the publique, which are inſeperable.</p>
                  <p>The clauſe in that Act, that no man ſhould ſue for grace or pardon for any offence condemned,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>R.</hi> 2.11. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> cap.</hi> 13. 4. <hi>pars in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. fol.</hi> 42.</note> or forfeiture given by that Act, was repealed by a ſubſequent Act in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> holden unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, without example and againſt the Law and cuſtom of the Parliament. This condemnes the Propoſition for diſabling the King to Pardon. 4. <hi>pars inſtit, fol.</hi> 42. The Act of 11. R. 2. ſo much urged by the other ſide, was an Act to the which the King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and ſo a perfect Act: yet Note the Army then about the Town: Note that that Law is againſt private perſons, and by the 3. <hi>cap.</hi> thereof, the Treaſons there declared, are declared to be new
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33168:16"/>Treaſons made by that Act, and not to be drawne to example, it was abrogated 21. R. 2. and revived by an uſurper 1. <hi>H.</hi> 4. to pleaſe the people, and by the tenth chap. thereof enacts that nothing ſhall be treaſon but what is declared by 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">16. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. cap.</hi> 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Regality of the Crown of England is immediatly ſubject to God and to none other. Plaine words,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>H.</hi> 4.</note> ſhewing where the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power is.</p>
                  <p>The Commiſſion of Array is in force and no other Commiſſion <hi>Ret. Parim.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>numb.</hi> 24. an Act not printed, this Act was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed by 4. and 5. P. <hi>&amp; M. cap.</hi> 2. this repealed by the Act of 1. <hi>Iacobi</hi> and ſo it is of force at this day, for the repealing Statute is repealed 4. <hi>pars inſtitu. fol.</hi> 51. <hi>&amp;</hi> 125. publiſhed ſithence this Parliament, by the deſire of the houſe of Commons, their Order is printed in the laſt leafe of the commentaries upon <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A booke alowed by Sir <hi>Nat. Brent,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the War: <hi>fol.</hi> 65.</note> by their party is holden for the Oracle of the Law, who wrote the ſaid fourth part, in a calme and quiet time, and I may ſay, when there was no need to defend the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Commiſſion of Array.</p>
                  <p>For that objection, that that Commiſsion leaves power to the Commiſsioners to tax men <hi>ſecundum facultates,</hi> and ſo make all mens eſtates Arbitrary: the Anſwer is, that in levying of publick ayds upon mens goods &amp; eſtates, which are variable, and probably cannot be certainly knowne by any but the owners, it is impoſsible to avoid diſcretion in the aſſeſſements, for ſo it ever was, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will be. By this appeares that the Votes of the two houſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the commiſsion of Array, were againſt the Law.</p>
                  <p>The death of the King diſſolves the Parliament,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>H.</hi> 5.</note> if Kings ſhould refer to the politique capacity it would continue after his death 4. <hi>pars Inſt.</hi> 46. which proves that the King cannot be ſaid to be there when he is abſent, as now he is:
<note place="margin">2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. 4 <hi>pars in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit</hi> 46.</note> there is no <hi>interregnum</hi> in the Kingdome the diſſolution of the Parliament by his death, ſhewes that the beginning and end thereof refers to the naturall perſon of the King, and therefore he may lawfully refuſe the Propoſitions.</p>
                  <p>2. H. 5. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. to the King only it belongs to make Leagues with Forraigne Princes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this ſhewes where the ſupreame power is.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33168:17"/>
                  <p>8. H. 6. <hi>numb.</hi> 57. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tt. Parl-Cookes</hi> 4. <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns inſtit.</hi> 25, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> peiviledge of Parliament is grantable for treaſon,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>H.</hi> 6.</note> Felony, or Breach of the Peace; if not to any one member, not to two, not to ten, not to the Major part, 19. H. 6.62. The Law is the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the King and his people by which they are ruled, King and people; And the people are by the law bound to ayde the King, and the King hath an inheritance to hould Parliaments and in the ayds granted by the Common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alty. If the major part of a Parliament commit treaſon they muſt not be Judges of it, for no man or body, can be Judge in his owne cauſe, and aſwell as ten or any number may commit treaſon, the greater number may aſwell.</p>
                  <p>The King by his letters pattents may conſtitute a County pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine and grant Regall rights,
<note place="margin">32. <hi>H.</hi> 6 13. <hi>Plowd.</hi> 334.</note> this ſhewes where the ſupreame power is.</p>
                  <p>17. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>rot parl. numb.</hi> 39.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ed</hi> 4.</note> No priviledge of Parliament is grantable for Treaſon, Fellony, or Breach of the peace, if not for one, not for two or more, or a Major part.</p>
                  <p>The ſame perſons muſt not be Judge and party. A corporate body can committ no treaſon,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Calvins Caſe</hi> 7 <hi>pars fol.</hi> 11 12</note> nor can treaſon be committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a corporate body, 21. E. 4, 13. ond 14. but the perſons of the men who make that body may committ treaſon, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it againſt the naturall perſon of him who to ſome purpoſes is a body corporate, but <hi>quatenus corporate</hi> no treaſon can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by or againſt ſuch a body; that body hath no ſoul, no life, and ſubſiſts only by the fiction of the Law, and for that reaſon the Law doth conclude as aforeſaid;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Plow. com.</hi> 213.</note> therefore the ſtatute of 25. E. 3. muſt be intended of the Kings naturall perſon conjoyned with the politique which are inſeparable and the Kings naturall perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Holmby, his politique is there alſo, and not at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;
<note place="margin">19. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.46.</note> for the politique and naturall make one body indiviſible.</p>
                  <p>If all the people of England ſhould breake the league made with a forreigne Prince,
<note place="margin">22. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>Fitz: ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſdiction. laſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite.</hi>
                     </note> without the Kings conſent, the league holds and is not broken; and therefore the repreſentative body is inferior to his Majeſties.</p>
                  <p>The King may erect a Court of Common-pleas in what part of the kingdome be pleaſeth by his letters patents; can the two hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes do the like?.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33168:17"/>
                  <p>1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 5. <hi>fol.</hi> 2. It cannot be ſaid that the King doth wrong,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ed.</hi> 5. 4 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.25. 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.29.</note> declared by all the Judges and Serjeants at law then there.</p>
                  <p>The reaſon is, nothing can be done in this Common wealth by the Kings grant or any other act of his, as to the ſubjects per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, goods, lands or liberties, but muſt be according to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed lawes, which the Judges are ſworn to obſerve and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver betwene the King and his people impartially to rich and poor, high and low; and therefore the Juſtices and the Miniſters of Juſtice are to be queſtioned and puniſhed if the Lawes be violated: And no reflection to be made on the King. All Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors and Judges for a yeare and three months untill the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults began this Parliament were all left to the ordinary courſe of Juſtice, what hath beene done ſithence is notorious.</p>
                  <p>For great Cauſes and conſiderations an act of Parliament was made for the ſurety of the ſaid Kings perſon;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>R.</hi> 3 1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> if a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were ſo tender of King <hi>Rich.</hi> the 3. the houſes have grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſon to care for the preſervation of his Majeſtie.</p>
                  <p>The Subjects are bound by their allegiance to ſerve the King for the time being againſt every Rebellion, power and might,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>H.</hi> 7. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> reared againſt him within this land, that it is againſt all lawes, reaſon and good canſcience, if the King ſhould happen to be vanquiſhed, that for the ſaid deede and true duty and alligeance they ſhould ſuffer in any thing, it is ordeined they ſhould not: and all acts of proceſſe of law hereafter to be made to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teary are to be void. This law is to be underſtood of the naturall perſon of the King, for his politique capacity cannot be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed; nor war reared againſt it.</p>
                  <p>Relapſers are to have no benefit of this act.</p>
                  <p>It is no ſtatute, if the King aſſent not to it,
<note place="margin">12 <hi>H.</hi> 7.20. <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> and he may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſent, this proves the negative voice.</p>
                  <p>The King hath full power in all cauſes to doe juſtice to all men this is affirmed of the King,
<note place="margin">24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> and not of the two Houſes.</p>
                  <p>The commons in Parliament acknowledg no ſuperior to the King under God, the houſes of Commons confeſſe the king to be above the repreſentative body of the Realme.</p>
                  <p>Of good right and equity the whol &amp; ſole power of pardning treaſons, fellonies &amp;c. belong to the King,
<note place="margin">27 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 24 <hi>Note.</hi>
                     </note> as alſo to make all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33168:18"/>Juſtices of Oyer &amp; Terminor, Judges, Juſtices of the peace, &amp;c. This law condemns the practiſe of both houſes at this time.</p>
                  <p>The kings royall aſſent to any Act of Parliament ſigned with his hand expreſſed in his Letters-patents under the great Seale, and declared to the Lords and Commons ſhall bee as effectuall,
<note place="margin">33 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21</note> as if he aſſented in his owne perſon; a vaine act if the King be virtually in the Houſes.</p>
                  <p>The King is the head of the Parliament, the Lords the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll members of the body,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dier</hi> 38. <hi>H.</hi> 8 <hi>fo</hi> 59.60.</note> the Commons the inferior members, and ſo the body is compoſed, therefore there is no more Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without a king, then there is a body without a head.</p>
                  <p>There is a corporation by the Common-law, as the King. Lords,
<note place="margin">14 <hi>H.</hi> 8 <hi>fol.</hi> 3.</note> and Commons, are a corporation in Parliament, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are no body without the King.</p>
                  <p>The death of the King diſchargeth all mainpriſe to appeare in any Court,
<note place="margin">24 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.48. 1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.2. 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7.10. 1 <hi>Ed</hi> 5.1.</note> or to keepe the Peace.</p>
                  <p>The death of the King diſcontinues all pleas by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-law, which agreeth not with the virtuall power inſiſted upon now.</p>
                  <p>Writs are diſcontinued by the death of the King;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> Patents of Judges, Commiſſion for Juſtices of the Peace, Sheriffs, Eſchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, determined by his death; Where is the virtuall power.</p>
                  <p>All authority and juriſdictions ſpirituall and temporall is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the King,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> therefore none from the Houſes.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſties ſubjects,
<note place="margin">2. 3 <hi>Ed</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 2 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe. <hi>Sa. pars Cooke</hi>
                     </note> according to their bounden duties, ought to ſerve the king in his warres, of this ſide or beyond the Seas; beyond the ſeas is to be underſtood for wages: This proves the power of warres, and preparation for war to be in the king.</p>
                  <p>It is moſt neceſſary both for common policy and duty of the ſubject,
<note place="margin">5. 6 <hi>Ed. cap.</hi> 11</note> to reſtrain all manner of ſhamefull ſtanders againſt their king, which when they be heard, cannot but be odible to his true and loving ſubjects, upon whom dependeth the whole unity &amp; univerſal weale of the realm. This condemns their continuing of the weekely pamphlets, who have been ſo foule mouthed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>The puniſhment of all offenders againſt the lawes, belongs to the king,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Q. Mary.</hi> 1 <hi>Mar. Pl.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2</note> and all juriſdictions doe, and of right ought to belong to the King. This leaves all to his Majeſty.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33168:18"/>
                  <p>All Commiſſions to levy men for the warre,
<note place="margin">4 5 <hi>P &amp;</hi> M. <hi>c.</hi> 3 <hi>Q. Eliz.</hi> 10 <hi>Eliz pl</hi> 315</note> are a warded by the king. The power of warre only belongs to the king.</p>
                  <p>It belongs to the king to defend his people, and to provide Armes and Force. No ſpeech of the two Houſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Roy ad ſole government de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſes ſubjects.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Plow.</hi> 234.242 213. <hi>Calvins caſe</hi> 7. <hi>pars fol</hi> 12. <hi>Plow. com.</hi> 213</note> Corps naturall le Roy &amp; politique ſunt un corps.</hi> that is, The king hath the ſole govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Subjects, the body politique and the naturall body of the king make one body and not divers, and are inſeparable and indiviſible.</p>
                  <p>The body naturall and politique make one body, and are not to be ſevered: Ligeance is due to the naturall body,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Plow.</hi> 934 243.213. <hi>Calvins caſe</hi> 7. <hi>pars fol.</hi> 12.</note> and is due by nature; Gods Law, and Mans law, cannot be forfeited nor renounced by any meanes, it is inſeparable from the perſon.</p>
                  <p>Every Member of the Houſe of Commons, at every Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, takes a corporall Oath.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Cawdries caſe.</hi> 5. <hi>pars fol.</hi> 1.</note> That the King is the Supreme and only Governour in all Cauſes, in all his Dominions, otherwiſe he is no Member of that Houſe; the words of the Law are, In all Cauſes, over all perſons.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid Act of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> is but declarative of the ancient Law, <hi>Cawdries</hi> Caſe <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Earle of Eſſex, and others, aſſembled multitudes of men to remove Councellors,
<note place="margin">43 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3 <hi>pars inſtit. fo,</hi> 6.2.</note> adjudged Treaſon by all the Judges of England.</p>
                  <p>To depoſe the king, or take him by force, to impriſon him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he hath yeelded to certain demands, adjudged Treaſon,
<note place="margin">39. <hi>Eliz. Hil.</hi> 1 <hi>Jacobi ibid.</hi>
                     </note> and adjudged accordingly in the Lord <hi>Cobhams</hi> Caſe.</p>
                  <p>Ariſing to alter Religion eſtabliſhed, or any Lawe, is Treaſon;
<note place="margin">39 <hi>Ed. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>adf. caſe f</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. By all the Judges of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>ibid.</hi> 10 <hi>Eliz Plow,</hi> 316.</note> ſo for taking of the Kings Caſtles, Forts, Ports or Shipping <hi>Brooke</hi> treaſon 24. 3 &amp; 4. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary, Dier, Staffords</hi> Caſe concerning Scarborough.</p>
                  <p>The Lawe makes not the ſervant greater then the Maſter, nor the ſubject greater then the King, for that were to ſubvert Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Meaſure.</p>
                  <p>The Law is not knowne but by Uſage,
<note place="margin">10 <hi>Eliz. Plow,</hi> 319.</note> and Uſage proves the Law, and how Uſage hath been is notoriouſly knowne.</p>
                  <p>The King is our only Rightfull and lawfull Liege Lord and Soveraigne,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>K. James.</hi> 1 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1. 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 8.</note> We doe upon the knees of our hearts ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ze con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Faith, Loyalty and Obedience to the King and his Royall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33168:19"/>progeny, in this high Court of Parliament, where all the body of the Realme is eyther in perſon or by repreſentation: We doe acknowledge that the true and ſincere Religion of the Church, is continued and eſtabliſhed by the King. And doe recognize, as we are bound by the Law of God and Man, the Realme of England and the Imperiall Crowne thereof doth belong to him by inherent byrth-right, and lawfull and undoubted ſucceſſion, and ſubmit our ſelves and our poſterities for ever, untill the laſt drop of our blood be ſpent, to his rule; and beſeech the king to accept the ſame as the firſt fruits of our Loyalty and Faith to his Majeſty and his poſteritie for ever, and for that this Act is not compleat nor perfect without his Majeſties aſſent, the ſame is humbly deſired. This proves that the Houſes are not above the King; that Kings have not their Titles to the Crowne by the two Houſes, but by inherent byrth-right, and that there can bee no Statute without his expreſſe aſſent, and deſtroyes the chyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra of the Kings virtuall being in the Houſes.</p>
                  <p>To promiſe obedience to the Pope, or any other State, Prince or Potentate,
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 4,</note> other then the King his Heires and Succeſſors, is Treaſon; and therefore thoſe perſons who call the Houſes the Eſtates offend this Lawe.</p>
                  <p>Such Bills as his Majeſty is bound in Conſcience and Juſtice to paſſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>K. Charles.</hi> Collection of Ordinances <hi>fo.</hi> 727. 1 <hi>pars ib. fol.</hi> 728.</note> are no Law without his aſſent.</p>
                  <p>To deſigne the ruine of the Kings perſon, or of Monarchy is a monſtrous and injurious charge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Lex non diſtinguit,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>ibid; fol.</hi> 865.</note> non eſt diſtinguendum,</hi> all the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Acts and Lawes doe evidently prove the Militia to belong to the king: that the king is not virtnally in the two Houſes: that the king is not conſiderable ſeparately in relation to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique capacity: that the king is not a perſon truſted with a power, but that it is his inherent byrth-right, from God, Nature and Lawe, and that hee hath not his power from the people: Theſe Lawes have none of thoſe diſtinctions of naturall and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, <hi>abſtractum &amp; concretum,</hi> power and perſon, in <hi>Caeſars</hi> time this Iſland had kings, and ever ſince, which is almoſt 17 hundred yeeres agoe.</p>
                  <p>No King can be named, in any time, made in this kingdom by the people: A parliament never made king, for they were kings
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33168:19"/>before, the Parliaments are ſummoned by the kings Writs, which for Knights Citizens and Burgeſſes begins thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex vic. Wilis. Saltem. Quia Nos de aviſamento &amp; aſſenſu conſilij nri. pro quibuſ. arduis &amp; urgentib. negetiis nos ſtatum &amp; defenſionem Regninri. Aug. &amp; Eccleſ. Anglic. concernentibus quoddam Parliamentum urum, apud B. teneri ordinavimus &amp; ibid cum Prelatis Magnatib. &amp; proceribus dicti Regni uri. Colloqui, habere &amp; tractatum, ipſi Vicecomiti precipimus firmiter injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo qd. facta Proclamatione in prox. Comitatu tuo poſt recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ejuſd. Brevis, dues Milites gladiis cinctos, &amp;c. eligi facias ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum hiis quae tunc ibidem de Communi Concilio nro. Angl faventi De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> contigerit ordinari ſuper Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis antedictis, ita quod pro defectis poteſtatis hujuſmodi ſeu propter improvidam electionem Milium, Civium, &amp; Burgenſium pred. dicta negotia ura. infecta non remanerent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King is <hi>Principium, caput &amp; finis Parliamenti,</hi> the body makes not the head,
<note place="margin">4 <hi>pars Inſtit: fol.</hi> 3 <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.</note> nor that which is <hi>poſterior</hi> that which is <hi>prior: concilium non eſt Preceptum, conciliarij non ſunt Praecepto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> for Counſell to compell a conſent, hath not beene heard of to this time in any age, and the houſe of Commons, by the writt, are not called ad <hi>concilium;</hi> the Writts to the twelve Judges, Kings Councell, twelve Maſters of the Chancery are <hi>concilium impenſuri,</hi> and ſo of the Peeres. The writts for the Cominalty, <hi>Ad faciendum &amp; conſentiendum.</hi> Which ſhewes what power the repreſentative body hath, they have not power to give an oath; neither do they claime it.
<note place="margin">The Oath of the Juſtices 18 of <hi>E.</hi> 3. among Statutes of that yeere.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King at all times, when there is no parliament, &amp; in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is aſſiſted with the advice of the Judges of the Lawe, 12 in number, for England at leaſt hath 2 Sergeants when few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: an Attorny and Solicitor, twelve Maſters of the Chancery, his Councell of State, conſiſting of ſome great Prelates and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Perſonages, verſed in State affaires, when they are feweſt to the number of twelve. All theſe perſons are alwaies of great ſubſtance, which is not preſerved but by the keeping of the Lawe, The Prelates verſed in divine Lawe, the other Grandees in affaires of State &amp; managery of Government. The Judges, Kings Sergeants, Attorny, Sollicitor, and Maſters of the Chancery verſed in the Lawe and Cuſtomes of the Realme: All
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33168:20"/>ſworn to ſerve the King and his people juſtly &amp; truly, the King is alſo ſworn to obſerve the Laws, and the Judges have in their Oath a clauſe, That they ſhall do common right to the Kings people, according to the eſtabliſhed Laws, not withſtanding any command of the King to the contrary, under the Great Seale or otherwiſe, The people are ſafe by the Lawes in force without any new: The Law finding the Kings of this Realme aſſiſted with ſo many great men of Conſcience, Honour and skill in the rule of Common-wealth, knowledge of the Lawes, and bound by the high and holy bond of an Oath upon the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, ſettles among other powers upon the King, a power to refuſe any Bill agreed upon by both Houſes, and power to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all offences, to paſſe any Graunts in his Minority, (there are many great perſons living hold many a thouſand pound a yeare by Patents from <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, paſſed when he was but ten yeares of age) not to be bound to any Law to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, whereby he doth not binde himſelfe; power of warre and peace, coyning of Money, making all Officers, &amp;c. The Lawe, for the reaſons aforeſaid, hath approved theſe powers to be unqueſtionable in the King, and all Kings have enjoyed them till 3. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1640.</p>
                  <p>It will bee ſaid notwithſtanding all this fence about the Lawes, the Lawes have beene violated, and therefore the ſaid powers muſt not hold, the two Houſes will remedy this.</p>
                  <p>The anſwere to this is evident: There is no time paſt, nor time preſent, nor will there bee time to come, ſo long as men mannage the Lawe, but the Lawes will be broken more or leſſe, as appeares by the ſtory of every age. All the pretended violations of this time were remedied by Acts to which the King conſented before his departure 10. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1641. being then driven away by Tumults. And the Houſes for a yeere and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt three Moneths: From 3. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1640 to 10 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1641. as aforeſaid, being a yeare and almoſt three moneths, had time and liberty to queſtion all thoſe perſons who were eyther cauſes or inſtruments of the violation of any of the Lawes.</p>
                  <p>Examine how both Houſes remedied them in former times. Firſt, touching Religion, What hath beens done this way? Both houſes in <hi>Henry</hi> the eights time tendred to him a Bill to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33168:20"/>bee paſſed called commonly the Bill of the ſix Articles, this was conceivd by them to be a juſt and a neceſſary Bill: Had not <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth done well to have refuſed the paſſing of this bill? both houſes tendred a bill to him to take the reading of the Scriptures from moſt of the laity: had not King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight deſerved much prayſe to reject this bill? In Queene <hi>Maryes</hi> time both houſes exhibited a bill to her to introduce the Popes pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the Roman Religion; had not Queen <hi>Mary</hi> done well to have refuſed this bill? Many ſuch inſtances may be given. The two Houſes now at Weſtminſter I am ſure will not deny but the refuſall of ſuch Bills had beene juſt, the King being aſſiſted as aforeſaid, and why not ſo in theſe times?</p>
                  <p>For the Civill Government what a bill did both houſes preſent to <hi>Richard</hi> the third, to make good his title to the Crowne; had it not beene great honour to him to have rejected it? what bills were exhibited to <hi>Henry</hi> the eight by both houſes for baſtardizing of his daughter <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a Queene of renowned memory, to ſettle the Crowne of this Relme, for default of Iſſue of his body, upon ſuch perſons as he ſhould declare by his letters Patents or his laſt will, and many more of the like? had not this refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of paſſing ſuch bills magnified his vertue and rendred him to poſterity in a different Character from what he now hath?</p>
                  <p>And by the experience of all times and the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of human frailty this concluſion is manifeſtly dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that it is not poſſible to keepe men at all times (be they the houſes, or the King and his councell) but there will be ſometimes ſome deviation from the Lawes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the conſtant and certain powers fixed by the ancient Law muſt not be made void, and the Kings Miniſters; the Laws do puniſh where the Law is tranſgreſſed, and they only ought to ſuffer for the ſame.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:33168:21"/>
                  <p>In this Parliament the houſes exhibited a bill to take away the ſuffrages of Biſhops in the upper houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and have ſithence agreed there ſhall be no more Biſhops at all, might not the King if he had ſo pleaſed have anſwered this bill with <hi>Le Roy s'aviſera,</hi> or <hi>no voult.</hi> it was againſt <hi>Magna Charta; Articuli Cleri</hi> and many other acts of Parliament. And might have farther given theſe reaſons if it had ſo pleaſed him for the ſame: firſt that this Bill deſtroyes the writt whereby they are made two houſes of Parliament the King in the writt to the Lords being <hi>Cum praelatis colloquium habere;</hi> ſecondly they have beene in all Parliaments ſince we had any, and voted, but in ſuch wherein they themſelves were concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: And there have beene Biſhops here ſithence we were Chriſtians, and the fundamentall Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome approves of them: if any of them were conceived offenſive; they were left to juſtice, and his Majeſtie would put in inoffenſive men in their places: but ſithence his Majeſtie hath paſſed the Bill for taking away their votes in Parliament, it is a Law that binds us ſo farr.</p>
                  <p>Upon the whole matter the Law hath notably deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that Bills agreed by both houſes, pretended to be for the publique good, are to be judged by the King, for in all Kings reigns Bills have been preferred by both houſes, which all wayes are pretended to be for the publique good, and many times are not, and were rejected with <hi>Roy s'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſera</hi> or <hi>Roy ne veult.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Parliament beganne the third of <hi>November</hi> 1640 before that time in all the Kings reigne no armed power did force any of the people to do any thing againſt the law: what was done, was by his Judges, officers Referees and Miniſters from that time untill the tenth of <hi>January</hi> 1641 (when the King went from London to avoyde the danger of frequent tumults, being a yeare and three months<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Privy Councellors and all his Juſtices and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33168:21"/>miniſters were left to the Juſtice of the law, there wanted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> time to puniſhable men.</p>
                  <p>The Sphaere of the houſe of Comment is to repreſent the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of the Countrey, to grant aydes for the King upon all fit occaſions extraordinary, to aſſent to the making or abrogating of lawes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Orb of the houſe of Lords to Reforme eroneous judgements given in the Kings Bench, to redreſſe the delayes of Courts of Juſtice, to receive all Petitions, to adviſe his Majeſtie with their Councell, to have their votes in making or abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Lawes, and to propoſe for the common good, what they conceive meete.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>x non cogit ad impoſſibilia,</hi> Subjects are not to expect from Kings impoſſible things, ſo many Judges, Councellours Sheriffes, Juſtices of the peace, Commiſſioners, Miniſters of State, that the King ſhould over-looke them all cannot be, it is impoſſible.</p>
                  <p>The King is virtually in his ordinary Courts of Juſtice; ſo long as they continue has Courts: their charge is to adminiſter the lawes in being, and not to delay, defarre or ſell-juſtice for any commandement of the King. We have Lawes enough <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ta b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i ſaculi ſunt boni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> good miniſters, as Judges and officers are many times wanting, the houſes propoſe now Lawes, or abrogation of the old; both induce novelty; the law for the reaſons aforeſaid, makes the King the only Judge, who is aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted therein by a great number of grave learned, and prudent men, as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>For the conſiderations aforeſaid the Kings party adhered to him, the law of the Land is their birth-right, their guide, no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is committed where that is not violated: they found the commiſſion of Array warranted by the law; they found the King in this Parliament to have quitted the Ship-money, Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood-money, ſeven Courts of Juſtice, conſented to a trienniall Parliament, ſetled the Foreſt bounds, tooke away the Clerke of the Market of the houſhold, truſted the houſe with the Navie, paſſed an Act not to diſſolve this Parliament without the Houſes aſſent; no people in the world ſo free if they could have been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33168:22"/>content with Lawes, oathes and reaſon, and nothing more could or can be deviſed to ſecure us, neither hath been in any time.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding all this we found the King driven from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> by frequent tumults, that two thirds and more of the Lords had diſſerted that houſe, for the ſame cauſe, and the greater part of the houſe of Commons left that houſe alſo for the ſame reaſon: new men choſen in their places, againſt Law, by the pretended Warrant of a counter ſet Seale; and in the Kings name againſt his conſent, levying warre againſt him, and ſeizing his Ports, Forts, Magazines and Revenue, and converting them to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and the ſubverſion of the Law and Land, laying taxes on the people, never heard of before in this Land; deviſed new oathes to oppoſe forces ray fed by the King, not to adhaere to him, but to them in this Warre which they call the Negative Oath, and the Vow and Covenant.</p>
                  <p>By ſeverall wayes never uſed in this Kingdome they have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed monies to foment this warre, and eſpecially to inrich ſome among them; namely firſt Exciſe, ſecondly Contributions, third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sequeſtrations, fourthly Fift parts, fiftly Twentieth Parts, fixtly Meale-money ſeventhly Sale of Plundered goods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ightly Loanes, ninthly Benevolences, tenthly, Collections upon their Faſt-dayes, eleventhly new Inpoſitions upon Merchandizes, twelvethly Guards maintained upon the charge of private men, thirteenthly Fifty Subſidies at one time, fourteenthly Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with ſuch as they call Delinquents, fifteenthly Sale of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops lands, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>From the Kings party meanes of ſubſiſtance are taken;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ract. li.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Stanford.</hi> 192. <hi>Sir Ger. Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods</hi> Caſe. 8. <hi>pars Cook</hi> 7. <hi>H.</hi> 4 <hi>laſt leaſe.</hi>
                     </note> before any indictment, their Lands ſeized, their goods taken, the Law allows a Traytor or Fellon attainted, <hi>Neceſſaria ſibi &amp; familie ſua in vict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtitu,</hi> where is the Covenant? where is the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of light? where is the liberty of the ſubject?</p>
                  <p>Firſt, We have ayded the King in this warre contrary to the negative oath and other votes, Our warrant is the twenty fifth of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, the ſecond Chapter, and the ſaid reſolutions of all the Judges.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33168:22"/>
                  <p>Secondly, Wee have maintained the Commiſſion of Array by the Kings Command, contrary to their votes: We are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the ſtatute of the fifth of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and the judgement of Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> the Oracle of the Law as they call him.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, We maintained Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, whom they would ſuppreſſe. Our warrant is <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtatutes more.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, we have maintained the booke of Common prayer, they ſuppreſſe it, Our warrant is five acts of Parliament in <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixt and Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, 5. <hi>Peſch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 35. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth inter placita Coronae in Banco Regis,</hi> New booke of Entries, ſol. 252. <hi>Penry,</hi> for publiſhing two ſcandalous Libels againſt the Church government, was indicted, arraigned, attainted, and executed at Tyburne.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, We maintained the Militia of the Kingdome to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the King, they the contrary, Our warrant is the ſtatute of the ſeventh of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and many ſtatures ſithence, the practiſe of all times, and the cuſtome of the Realm.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, We maintained the counterfeiting of the great Seale to be high Treaſon, and ſo of the uſurpation of the Kings Forts, Ports, Shipping, Caſtles and his Revenue, and the Coyning of money, againſt them; We have our warrant by the ſaid ſtatute of the twenty fifth of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, Chapter the ſecond, and divers others ſince, and the practiſe of all times.</p>
                  <p>Seventhly, We maintaine that the King is the only ſupreme go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermour in all cauſes. They, that his Majeſly is to be governed by them, Our warrant is the ſtatures of the firſt of Q. <hi>Eliza.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt, and the fifth of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Eighthly,
<note place="margin">9. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>ſol.</hi> 4.</note> Wee maintaine that the King is King by an inhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent birth-right; by nature, by Gods law, and by the lay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Land, They ſay his Kingly right is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Our warrant is the ſtatute of the firſt of King <hi>Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Chapter the firſt. And the reſolution of all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Calvins</hi> caſe.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33168:23"/>
                  <p>Ninthly We maintain that the politick capacity i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the naturall. They hold the contrary: Our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant is two flatures <hi>(viz.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>xilium Hugonis in Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds time, and the firſt of <hi>Edward</hi> the third Chapter the ſecond, and their Oracle who hath publiſhed it to poſterity, that it is damnable, deteſtable and execrable Treaſon, <hi>Calvins</hi> caſe <hi>pars</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>Tenthly we maintain that who aids the King at home or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad ought not to be moleſted or queſtioned for the ſame, they hold and practiſe the contrary, our warrant is the ſtatute of the eleventh of. <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh. Chapter the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Eleventhly We maintain that the King hath power to diſaſſent to any Bill agreed by the two Houſes; which they deny. Our warrant is the Statute of the ſecond of <hi>Henry</hi> the fift and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all times, the firſt of King <hi>Charles,</hi> Chapter the ſeventh the firſt of King <hi>James</hi> Chapter the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Twelfthly We maintain that Parliaments ought to be holden in a grave and peaceable manner, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ults, They allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed multitudes of the meaneſt ſort of people to come to <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> to cry for,
<note place="margin">Coll. of Ord. <hi>fol.</hi> 31.</note> Juſtice when they could not have their will, and keep guards of armed men to wait upon them. Our warrant is the Statute of the ſeventh of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond and their Oracle.</p>
                  <p>Thirteenthly We maintain that there is no ſtate within this Kingdome but the Kings Majeſty, and that to adhere to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther State within this Kingdome is high treaſon, our warrant is the Statute of the third of King <hi>James</hi> Chapter the fourth, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>enty third of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Chapter the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Fourteenthly, We maintain that to levy a warre to remove Councellours, to alter religion, or any Law eſtabliſhed is high Treaſon, They hold the contrary. <hi>One warrant is</hi> the reſolutions of all the judges of <hi>England</hi> in Queen <hi>Eliſabeths</hi> time, and their oracle agrees with the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Fifteenthly We maintain that no man ſhould be impriſoned, put out of his Lands, but by due courſe of Law, and that no man ought to be adjudged to death but by the Law eſtabliſhed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33168:23"/>the cuſtomer of the Realm, or by act of Parliament; They pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe the contrary in <hi>London, Briſtol, Kent, &amp;c. Our</hi> warrant is <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Chapter the twenty ninth, the <hi>Petition of right</hi> the third of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and divers Lawes there mentioned.</p>
                  <p>We of the Kings party, did and do deteſt Monopolies, and ſhip money, and all the grievances of the people as much as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men living, we do well know that our eſtates, lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are preſerved by the Lawes, and that the King is bound by his lawes, we love Parliaments, if the Kings, Judges, Counſell or Miniſters have done amiſſe, they had from the third of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1640 to the tenth of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1641 time to puniſh them, being all left to Juſtice where is the Kings fault?</p>
                  <p>The law faith the King can do no wrong,
<note place="margin">11 <hi>pars Cooks Reports Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen Colledge</hi> Cale.</note> that he is <hi>medicus Regni, pater patriae ſponſus regni qui per annlum</hi> is eſpouſed to his Realm at his Coronation; The King is Gods Lieutenant, and is not able to do an unjuſt thing, theſe are the words of the Law.</p>
                  <p>One great matter is pretended that the people are not ſure to enjoy the acts paſſed this Parliament, A ſucceeding Parliament may repeal them; The objection is very weak, a Parliament ſucceeding to that may repeal that repealing Parliament. That feare is endleſſe and remedileſſe, for it is the eſſence of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being compleat and as they ought to be, of head, and all the Members, to have power over Parliaments before; Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are as the time are; if a turbulent faction prevails the Parliaments are wicked as appears by the examples recited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of extreme wicked Parliaments: if the times be ſober and modeſt, prudent and not biaſſed, the Parliaments are right good, and honourable, and they are good medicines and ſalves, but in this Parliament <hi>exceſſit medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a medum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this cauſe and warre between the Kings Majeſty, and the two Houſes at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> what guide had the Subjects of the Land to direct them but the lawes? What means could they uſe to diſcern what to follow, what to avoid but the Lawes? The King declaresi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> treaſon to adhere to the Houſes in this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33168:24"/>warre: The Houſes declare it Treaſon to adhere to the King in this Warre. The Subjects for a great and conſiderable part of them (treaſon being ſuch a crime as forfets life and eſtate, alſo renders a mans poſterity baſe beggerly and infamous) looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lawes, and find the letter of the law requires them to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the King, as before is manifeſted, was ever ſubject criminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſht in any age or nation for his purſuit of what the letter of the Law commands?</p>
                  <p>The Subjects of the kingdome find the diſtinction and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation now put upon the Lawes of <hi>Abſtractum &amp; Concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> Power and Perſon, body politique, and naturall, Perſonall preſence and virtuall, to have beene condemned by the law: And ſo the Kings party hath both the letter of the law and the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the letter cleared to their judgements, whereby they might evidently perceive what ſide to adhaere to, what ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction could modeſt peaceable and loyall men more deſire?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A verbo legis in criminibus &amp; poenis non eſt recedendum,</hi> hath been an approved maxime of law in all ages and times. If the King be King and remain in his Kingly office (as they call it) then all the ſaid lawes are againſt them without colour:
<note place="margin">Coll of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances 777.</note> they ſay the ſaid lawes relate to him in his Office, they cannot ſay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, Commiſſions and pardon in the Kings name, and the perſon of the King and his body politique cannot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor ought to be ſevered as hath beene before declared:
<note place="margin">5 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</note> And the members of both houſes have ſworn conſtantly in this Parliament that the King is the only ſupreme Governour in all cauſes over all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at this preſent time.</p>
                  <p>For that of verball or perſonall commands of the King which is objected, We affirme few things to be ſubject thereto by the law: But his Majeſties Command under his great Seale, which in this warre hath beene uſed by the Kings command for his Commiſſion to leavy and array men, that is no perſonall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (which the law in ſome caſes diſallowes) but that is ſuch a command, ſo made, as all men hold their lands by, who hold by Patents; All corporations have their Charters which hold
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33168:24"/>by Charters, and all Judges and officers their places and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
                  <p>It is objected the King cannot ſuppreſſe his Courts of Juſtice,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ob. Sol.</hi> 7 <hi>pars</hi> The Earle of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlands Caſe. 1 <hi>Eliz. Dier.</hi> 165.7. <hi>pars Cooke.</hi>
                     </note> and that this warre tended to their ſuppreſſion.</p>
                  <p>The anſwer is the King cannot nor ought to ſuppreſſe Juſtice or his Courts of Juſtice, nor ever did: But Courts of Juſtice by <hi>abuſer or non uſer</hi> ceaſe to be courts of Juſtice; when Judges are made and proceedings in thoſe courts holden by others then Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges made by the King, and againſt his command under the great Seale, and his Majeſtie is not obeyed, but the votes of the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<note place="margin">The caſe of diſcontinuance of Proceſſe.</note> they ceaſe to be the Kings Courts and are become the Courts of the houſes, and his Judges breaking that condition in law, of truſt and loyalty, implied in their Patents, are no longer his Judges; they obey and exerciſe their places by vertue of writts and proceſſes under a counterfet Seale. The King only can make Judges, the twenty ſeventh of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, Chapter the twenty fourth, <hi>Iuſtices of the peace, &amp;c.</hi> twenty eighth of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth <hi>Dier</hi> the eleventh, the Kings Patent makes Judges: The cheeſe Juſtice of the Kings Bench is made by the Kings writ only of all the judges.</p>
                  <p>The great Seale is the key of the kingdome,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Articuli ſuper chartas cap.</hi> 5.</note> and meet it is that the King ſhould have the key of his kingdome about him; 2. <hi>pars inſtit</hi> 552. which confutes their ſaying that the King got the Seale away ſurreptitiouſly.</p>
                  <p>The King, and he only,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Britton ſol.</hi> 23.</note> may remove his Courts from Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter into ſome other place, at Yorke the Termes were kept for ſeaven yeares, in <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt's time: but for the Court of Common pleas, the place muſt be certaine; for the Kings Bench and Chancery, the King by the law may command them to attend his perſon alwayes if it ſeeme ſo meete unto him: but the removing of the Common pleas muſt be to a place certaine and ſo notified to the people.</p>
                  <p>All the bookes of law in all times agree,
<note place="margin">34. <hi>Aſſis. pl.</hi> 24.22. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>Fitz. juriſdiction laſt placit.</hi>
                     </note> that the King may grant conuſance of all Pleas at his pleaſure within any County or precinct to be holden there only, and remove the Courts from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33168:25"/>Weſtminſter to ſome other place (for the Common Pleas,
<note place="margin">6 <hi>H.</hi> 7.9.6 <hi>Eliz. Dier.</hi> 226.</note> the place muſt be certaine, and ſo notified to the people) and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe the termes as he ſees cauſe. All which the two houſes have violated. <hi>Plebs ſine lege ruis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some ſeeming objections of Maſter <hi>Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'s,</hi> ſcattered in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers books anſwered, and the truth thereby more fully clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth reviveth the ſtatute of the eleventh of <hi>Richard</hi> ſecond,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> and repeales to the twelfth of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, whereby certaine perſons were declared traytors to the King and Kingdome, being of the Kings party.</p>
                  <p>True,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> but note, the eleventh of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, A Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment beſet with 40000 men, and the King aſſents to it ſo an Act, and beſides the firſt of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth declares, that the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons mentioned in the act of the eleventh of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, being but againſt a few private men ſhall not be drawn into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and that no Treaſon ſhould be but ſuch as the twenty fift of <hi>Edward</hi> the third declares.
<note place="margin">9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>ſol.</hi> 80.</note> All theſe are Acts paſſed by the King and the three eſtates, not to be drawne into example, in a tumultuous time, by a beſieged Parliament, with an army, and the confirmer of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth being an uſurper makes that Act of the firſt of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth to ſecure himſelfe. Alſo what is this in the votes of the two houſes only at this time.</p>
                  <p>The Court of Parliament is above the King,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> for it may avoid his Charters Commiſſions, &amp;c. granted againſt the law.</p>
                  <p>And the Law is above the King.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the ſame reaſon you may ſay that the Courts of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, or any of the Courts of Law at <hi>Weſtminster</hi> are above the King, for they make of no effect the Kings Charters, which are paſſed againſt the Law: and the King is Subject to Law, and ſworne to maintaine it. Again, it is no Parliament without the King, and the King is the head thereof, he is <hi>principium Caput &amp; finis</hi> of a Parliament, as <hi>Medas tenends Parliament.</hi> hath it, and two houſes only, want <hi>principium Caput &amp; fixis</hi> of a Parliament
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33168:25"/>and it is a ſorry Parliament that wants all theſe. And therefore to ſay that Parliaments are above the King, is to ſay that the King is above himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>The Parliament can enlarge the Kings prerogative,
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is above him.</p>
                  <p>If the King aſſent, otherwiſe not;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> and then it is an Act of Parliament, and otherwiſe no Act.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, God, the Law, and the Kings Court,
<note place="margin">4 <hi>Ob</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>(viz.)</hi> his Earles and Barons are above the King, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in Parliament, as Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> expounds it.</p>
                  <p>Where is then the Houſe of Commons? Indeed, take God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> the Law, and Earles and Barons together it is true; but to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the Earles and Barons in Parliament are above the King (the King being the head of the Parliament, and they one of the members) how an inferior member is above the head, is hard to conceive: beſides, that poſition deſtroyes all M. <hi>Pry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es</hi> diſcourſe, who attributes ſo much to the Houſe of Commons.</p>
                  <p>The King is but one of the three eſtates of Parliament,
<note place="margin">5 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> and two are greater then one; therefore above.</p>
                  <p>The Legs, Armes,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> and Trunke of the Body are greater then the Head, and yet not above; nor with life, without it: the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument holds for quantitie, but not for qualitie; and in truth, the King is none of the three eſtates, but above them all; the three eſtates are, the Lords Spirituall, the Lords Temporall, and the Commons; <hi>Coke,</hi> their Oracle, in his Chapter of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, <hi>fol.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>In Corporations,
<note place="margin">6 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> the greater number of voyces make all the Acts of the Corporation valid; therefore ſo in Parliament.</p>
                  <p>By this reaſon the Kings aſſent is needleſſe, and to no end,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> and all the Acts of Parliament formerly mentioned, and Law-Bookes have quite miſtaken the matter, which with unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous voyce requires the Kings aſſent as neceſſarie: beſides, the Corporations are ſo conſtituted by the Kings Charters, that the greater number of Votes ſhall make their Acts valid.</p>
                  <p>The King, as King,
<note place="margin">7 Ob.</note> is preſent in his Parliament as well as in all other his Courts of Juſtice, how be it he is not ther.</p>
                  <p>In his other Courts of Juſtice he hath no voye,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> he is none
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33168:26"/>of the Judges, in the Parliament he hath; if his preſence be not neceſſarie, his voyce is not, nor his aſſent.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Ob.</hi> Soverain power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6, 47.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The originall prime legiſlative power of making Lawes to bind the ſubjects and their poſteritie, reſts not in the King, but in the Kingdome and Parliament, which repreſents it.</p>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> in the ſame leafe affirmes, and truly, that the Kings aſſent is generally requiſite to paſſe Lawes and ratifie them;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> the King is the head of the Kingdome and Parliament, how then can a Body act without a Head?</p>
                  <p>A <hi>major</hi> part of a Corporation binds,
<note place="margin">9 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> therefore the <hi>major</hi> part in Parliament, and ſo of by-Lawes.</p>
                  <p>The Corporation is ſo bound, either by the Kings Charters,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> or by preſcription, which ſometimes had the Kings conceſſion; but preſcription, and Law, and practiſe, alwayes left the King a negative voyce.</p>
                  <p>The King cannot alter the Bills preſented to him by both Houſes,
<note place="margin">10 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
                  <p>True;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> but the King may refuſe them.</p>
                  <p>Acts of Parliament and Lawes miniſtred in the Reignes of Uſurpers,
<note place="margin">11 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> bind rightfull Kings, g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
                  <p>What is this to prove the two Houſes power only,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> which is the queſtion? A King <hi>de facto</hi> muſt be obeyed by them who ſubmitted to him, and they are his Subjects by their ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not Subjects <hi>de facto</hi> to the true King, and ſuch being Traytors and Rebels to the Regent King (having renounced the true King) when the lawfull King is reſtored,
<note place="margin">9. Id. 4.12</note> may be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by him for their Treaſon againſt the Uſurper. But here is a King ſtill in both caſes, and the proceedings at Law holds; the Judges having their Patents from the being Kings, in the reignes of Kings, <hi>de facto</hi> or <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> for all Kings are bound and ſworne to obſerve the Lawes.</p>
                  <p>A King dies without Heire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <note place="margin">12 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> is an infant, <hi>non compes mentis, &amp;c.</hi> the two Houſes may eſtabliſh Lawes. g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
                  <p>There is no <hi>Inter-regnum</hi> in <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> as appeares by all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bookes of Law; and therefore the dying without Hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is a vaine ſuppoſition, and by their principle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is conſiderable in his politique capacitie, which cannot die at alſo The Protector,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33168:26"/>aſſiſted by the Councell of the King at Law, his twelve Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the Countell of State, his Attorney, Solicitor, and two Sergeants at Law, his twelve Maſters of the Chancerie, hath in the Kings behalfe, and ever had, a negative Voyce: but what is thi no the preſent queſtion? Wee have a King of fall age, of great wiſdome and judgement; the power of the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in ſuch a caſe to be over the King, cannot be ſhowne.</p>
                  <p>The King cannot diſ-aſſent to publique and neceſſarie Bills for the common good, g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.
<note place="margin">13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor ever did good King: but who ſhall be judge,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> whether they be publique and neceſſarie? The <hi>major</hi> part in either of the Houſes, for paſſing of Bills ſo pretended, may be but one or two voyces, or very few, and perhaps of no judicious men: is it not then fitter or more agreeable to reaſon, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie and Councell of State, his twelve Judges, his Sergeants, Attorney and Solicitor, twelve Maſters of the Chancerie, ſhould judge of the conveniencie and benefit of ſuch Bills for the publique good, rather then a <hi>minor,</hi> (of which ſort there may be in the Houſes) or a weake man, or a few, who often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times carry it by making the <hi>major</hi> part, which involves the conſent of all? let reaſon determine.</p>
                  <p>The Kings of <hi>England</hi> have beene elective;
<note place="margin">14 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> and the King by his Coronation-Oath is bound to maintaine <hi>juſtas leges &amp; conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tudines quas vulgas elegerit,</hi> g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>perie</hi> hath beene in the kingdome,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> and therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it ſtill, will not be taken for a good argument; when things are ſetled for many ages, to look back to times of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion is to deſtroy all repoſe: The Act of Parliament, of the firſt of <hi>K. James,</hi> Chapter the firſt, and all our extant <hi>Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> ſay, that the Kings Office is an heritage inherent in the bloud of our Kings, and their birth-right.</p>
                  <p>And Uſurpers that come in by the conſent of the people are <hi>Kings de facto,</hi> but not <hi>de jure,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ed. 4. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> but not <hi>de jure,</hi> as appeares by the Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament declaring them ſo: And by all our Law-Bookes and the fundamentall conſtitution of the Land, Regall power is hereditarie and not elective.</p>
                  <p>For the words <hi>(vulgus-elegerit)</hi> if <hi>vulgus</hi> be applyed to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33168:27"/>Houſe of Commons,
<note place="margin">1 H. 7.</note> they of themſelves can make no Lawes. The Peeres were never yet tearmed <hi>vulgus;</hi> but allowing they be ſo called, the Lawes to be made muſt be juſt; and who is fit to judge thereof, is before made evident.</p>
                  <p>Cuſtomes cannot referre to future time,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> and both are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled, Lawes and Cuſtomes.</p>
                  <p>Princes have beene depoſed, and may be by the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
                  <p>The depoſers were Traytors,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> as appeares by the reſolution of all the Judges of <hi>England; Coke,</hi> Chap. Treaſon, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the Inſtitutes. And never was King depoſed but in tumultuous and mad times, and by the power of Armies, and they who were to be the ſucceeding Kings in the head of them, as <hi>Edward</hi> the third and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth.</p>
                  <p>The appeale to the Parliament for errors in judgements in all Courts,
<note place="margin">16 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> is frequent, g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
                  <p>This is onely to the Houſe of Lords,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> and that is not the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; the Houſe of Commons have nothing to doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: and in the Houſe of Peeres, if a Writ of Error be brought to reverſe any judgement, there is firſt a petition to the King for the allowance thereof; and the reaſon of the Law in this caſe is, for that the Judges of the Land all of them, the Kings Councell and twelve Maſters of the Chancerie aſſiſt there, by whoſe advice erroneous judgements are redreſſed.</p>
                  <p>The Parliaments have determined of the rights of Kings,
<note place="margin">17 <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> as in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixts time, and others; and Parliaments have bound the ſucceſſion of Kings, as appeares by the Statute of the thirteenth of <hi>Q. Elizab.</hi> Chapter the firſt: and the diſcent of the Crowne is guided rather by a Parliamentarie Title then by Common Law, g<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
                  <p>If this Objection be true,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> that the Title to the Crowne is by Parliament, then we had no Uſurpers, for they all had Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to back them, yea, <hi>Richard</hi> the third, that Monſter. All cur Bookes of Law ſay they have the Crowne by diſcent, and the Statutes of the Land declare, that they have the ſame by inherent birth-right. And the Statute of the thirteenth of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> the firſt Chapter, was made to ſecure Q, <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33168:27"/>againſt the Qu. of <hi>Sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> then in the kingdome, clayming the Grown of <hi>England,</hi> and having many adherent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> And that Statute to that end a firmes no ſuch power in the two Hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for (which is the Queſtion) but in <hi>Q Elizabeth,</hi> and the two Houſes, which makes againſt the pretence of this time.</p>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Prynne, fol.</hi> 104. of his booke, intituled, <hi>The Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments ſupreme power, &amp;c.</hi> Objecting the Statute of the firſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and his own Oath, that the king is the onely ſupreme Governour of this Realme; Anſwers, The Parliament is the ſupreme power, and the king ſupreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour: And yet there he allowes him a Negative Voyce; and <hi>fol.</hi> 107. confeſſeth that Acts of Parliament tranſlated the Crowne from the right Heires at Common-law, to others who had no good Title; then the Parliamentary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Title makes not the king, ſo powerfull in truth, that it eſcapes from a man unawares: To make a diſtinction betweene Supreme Governour, and Supreme power, is very ſtrange, for who can Governe without power?</p>
                  <p>The king aſſembles the Parliament by His Writ, adjourns,
<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Speed</hi> 645.4 par. Inſtit. 27. &amp; 1.</note> prorogues, and diſſolves the Parliament, by the law at his pleaſure, as is evident by conſtant practiſe, the Houſe of Commons never ſate after an adjournment of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the kings command. Where is the ſupreme Power.</p>
                  <p>The king by his Oath;
<note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> is bound to deny no man right much leſſe the Parliament, to agree to all juſt and neceſſary lawes propoſed by them to the king. This is the ſubſtance of the diſcourſe againſt the kings Negative Voyce.</p>
                  <p>The king is ſo bound as is ſet downe in the Objection, but who ſhall judge whether the Bill propoſed be juſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> For all that they doe propoſe are ſo pretended and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in either Houſe, ſometimes by one or two Voyces; or ſome few as aforeſaid, and certainly as hath been ſhewn, the king, his Councell of State, his Judges, Sargeants, Attorney, Sollicitor, and twelve Maſters of the Chatcery can better judge of them, then two or three, or few more.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Pryn fol.</hi> 45. In his book of the Parliaments intereſt to nominate Privie-Councellors, calleth the opinion of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33168:28"/>
                     <hi>Spencers,</hi> to divide the Perſon of the King from his Crowne, a ſtrange opinion,
<note place="margin">Calvins caſe, 7. pars, fol. 11.</note> and cites <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe, but leaves out the concluſions there in mentioned, <hi>fol.</hi> 15. Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> ſaith there, But let this opinion bee what it will: without the Kings Grace and Pardon it will goe very far, and two Acts of Parliament there mentioned are beyond an opinion. And in his Book of the opening of the Great Scale, <hi>fol.</hi> 17. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath no juriſdiction to uſe the Great Seale for Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons Generall or Particular. Where is the Supreme power?</p>
                  <p>Mr.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9. <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Prynnes</hi> (opening of the Seale) <hi>pag.</hi> 19. ſaith, The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen and State, the day after the Funerall of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third (King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt his ſonne being in the Holy Land) made a new Great Seale, and Keepers of the ſame: And in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixts time, in the firſt yeere of his Reigne, the like was done in Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A facto,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sol.</hi>
                        </note> ad jus,</hi> is no good Argument, for that in <hi>Edward</hi> the firſts time, it was no Parliament, for King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. was dead, which diſſolved the Parliament, if called in his time, and it could be no Parliament of Edward the firſts time, for no Writ iſſued to ſummon a Parliament in his Name, nor could iſſue but under that New Seale, it was ſo ſodainly done after <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds death, King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in the Holy Land, it was the firſt yeere of his Reign, and no Parliament was held that yeere, nor the ſecond yeere of his Reigne: The firſt Parliament that was in his Reigne, was in the third yeere of his Reigne, as appeares by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Acts. Alſo the making of that Seale was by ſome Lords then preſent, What hand had the Commons in it? Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Seale made in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixths time, the Protector was Vice-Roy according to the courſe of Law, and ſo the making of that Seal was by the Protector in the Kings name; and that Protector, <hi>Humphrey</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> as Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, in the kings Name ſummoned that Parliament, and was Protector made by the Lords, and not in Parliament, as appeareth plainely, for that Parliament was in the firſt of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, and the firſt holden in his time, and power given by Commiſſion to the ſaid Duke, then Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33168:28"/>to ſummon that Parliament, <hi>Prynne, ibid. fol.</hi> 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t the new count c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe it Seale was made when the King was at <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>xford,</hi> in his own kingdome, and not in the holy Land.</p>
                  <p>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Prynne</hi> in his Book of the two Houſes power to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Taxes, reſtraines Malignants againſt any <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">20. <hi>Ob.</hi>
                     </note> &amp;c. ſaith, that the Parliament is above <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and <hi>fol.</hi> 15. <hi>ibid.</hi> The Parliament hath power over <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to repeale the ſame when there is Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>This Argument ſuppoſeth that they have the kings power,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sol.</hi>
                     </note> which hath appeared formerly they have not. But ſuppoſe they had, <hi>Magna Charta</hi> containes many morall Lawes, which by the Law of the Land a Parliament cannot alter, 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.2. <hi>D. &amp; Student,</hi> 2. <hi>Dialogue.</hi> For example it ſaith <hi>cap</hi> 18 Juſtice ſhall not be ſold, delayed, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> denyed to any man: but by this Argument the Parliament may make law to delay, deny, and to ſell Juſtice, which ſurely is a very ill poſition to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
                  <p>What they would have doth now by the Propoſitions ſent to <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> caſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to his Majeſty appeare, whereby they would have him diveſt himſelfe, and ſettle in them all his kingly power by Sea and land, and of themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o have power, without him, today upon the people of this land what taxes they think meet, to aboliſh the Common, prayer booke, to aboliſh Epiſcopacie, and to introduce a Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not yet agreed, but ſuch as they ſhall agree on.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y finding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> prevailing p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rty in both Houſes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and being chaſed away with Tumults from <hi>London,</hi> leaves the Houſes for theſe Reaſons, <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Government for Religion, in againſt the king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, againſt their Oathes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For every of them hath ſworne in this Parliament, That His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſty is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſupreme Governour in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſticall and over all perſons.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, This courſe is againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the 1. chap. and the laſt. <hi>Salvae ſuis Epiſcopis omnes libertates ſuae,</hi> Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by thirty two Acts of Parliament; and in the two and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33168:29"/>fortieth of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in the firſt Chapter enacts; If any Statute be made to the contrary, it ſhall be holden for none, and ſo it is for Judgements at Law, in the 25. of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the 1. chap. 1, 2. The Great Charter is declared to bee the Common Law of the Land.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, they endeavour to take away by their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, the Government of Biſhops, which is as ancient as Chriſtianity in this Land, and the Book of Common-Prayer ſetled by five Acts of Parliament, and compiled by the Reformers and Martyrs, and practiſed in the time of foure Princes.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, theſe Propoſitions taking away from His Majeſty all his power by land and Sea, rob him of that which all his Anceſtours, kings of this Realme, have enjoyed. That En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment and Uſage makes the Law, and a Right, by the ſame to His Majeſty. They are againſt their owne Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made this Parliament, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to maintaine His Royall perſon, Honour, and Eſtate; They are againſt their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which doth ſay, that they will not diminiſh His Juſt Power and Greatneſſe.</p>
                  <p>For theſe Reaſons His Majeſty hath left them, and as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beleeved, will refuſe to agree to the ſaid Propoſitions, as by the Fundamentall Law of the land hee may (having a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Voyce) to any Bills propoſed.</p>
                  <p>The reſult of all is, upon the whole matter: That the king thus leaving of the Houſes, and his Denyall to paſſe the ſaid Propoſitions, are ſo farre from making him a Tyrant, or not in a condition to Governe, at the preſent; That thereby hee is rendred a Juſt, Magnanimous, and pious Prince: ſo that by this it appeares clearly to whom the Miſeries of theſe Times are to be imputed. The remedy for all, is, an Act of Oblivion, and a Generall pardon.</p>
                  <closer>God ſave the KING.</closer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>DAVID, JENKINS, <hi>now Priſoner in the Tower.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <date>28, <hi>Aprilis,</hi> 1647.</date>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE CORDIALL OF JVDGE <hi>JENKINS,</hi> For the good People of LONDON; In Reply to a thing, called, AN Anſwer to the Poyſonous Seditious Paper of Mr <hi>David Jenkins;</hi> By <hi>H.P.</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſter of <hi>Lincolns-Inne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:30"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33168:30"/>
                  <head>The Cordial of <hi>Judge Jenkings</hi> for the good People of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>After the ſaid Mr <hi>H.P.</hi> hath made a recitall of the Heads of my <hi>Vindication,</hi> hee deduceth his Anſwer unto theſe eight Particulars, which follow <hi>verbatum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It cannot be denyed, but the</hi> Parliament <hi>ſits by the Kings Writ, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ay if Statute Law be greater then the</hi> Kings <hi>Writ, it cannot be denyed but the</hi> Parliament <hi>ſits or ought to ſit by ſomething greater then the</hi> Kings <hi>Writ; And, if it be confeſſed that the</hi> Parliament <hi>ſits by the</hi> Kings <hi>Writ, but does not Act by the</hi> Kings <hi>Writ, then it muſt follow that the</hi> Parliament <hi>is a void vaine Court, and ſits to no purpoſe; nay it muſt alſo follow, that the</hi> Parliament <hi>is of leſſe authority, and of leſſe uſe then any other inferiour Court; foraſmuch as it is not in the</hi> Kings <hi>power to controule other Courts, or to prevent them from ſitting or Acting.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This is a groſſe</hi> non ſequitur, <hi>the</hi> Kings <hi>power is in himſelf;</hi> Ergo, <hi>it is not derived to, nor does reſide virtually in the</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. <hi>For the light of the Sun remaines imbodied, and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted in the Globe of the Sun, at the ſame time as it is diffuſed and diſplayed through all the body of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yre; and who ſees not that the King without emptying himſelfe, gives commiſſions daily of Oyer and Terminer to others, which yet he himſelfe can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruſtrate nor clude? but for my part I conceive it is a great errour to inferre that the</hi> Parliament <hi>has onely the</hi> Kings <hi>power, becauſe it has the Kings power in it: for it ſeemes to me, that the</hi>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:33168:31"/>
                        <hi>Parliament</hi> does both ſit and act by concurrent power, devolved both from the King and Kingdom; And this in ſome things is more obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and apparent then in others. For by what power does the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> grant Subſidies to the King? if only by the power which the King gives, then the King may take Subſidies without any grant from the Parliament: and if it be ſo by a power which the people give to the Parliament; Then it will follow the Parliament has a power given both by King and Kingdome.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <p>The ſending Propoſitions to the King, and deſiring his concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, is ſcarce worth an Anſwer; for Subjects may humbly petition for that which is their ſtrict right and property. Nay, it may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times beſeeme a ſuperiour to preferre ſuite to an inferiour for matters in themſelves du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. God himſelfe has not utterly diſdained to beſeech his own miſerable impious unworthy creatures: beſides, tis not our Tenet, that the King has no power, becauſe he has not all power, nor that the King cannot at all promote our happineſſe, becauſe hee has no juſt claime to procure our ruine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <p>We affirm not, that the Kings power is ſeparated from his Perſon, ſo as the two <hi>Spencers</hi> affirmed, neither doe we frame concluſions out of that ſeparation, as the two <hi>Spencers</hi> did, either that the King may be removed for miſdemeanours, or reformed <hi>per aſpertè</hi> or that the Subject is bound to govern in ayde of him; we only ſay, that his power is diſtinguiſhable from his perſon, and when he himſelf makes a diſtinction betwixt them, commanding <hi>one thing</hi> by his Legall Writs, Courts, and Officers, and commanding <hi>another thing</hi> extrajudically by word of mouth, Letters, or Miniſters, we are to obey his power rather then his perſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="part">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <p>We take not from the King all power of pardoning Delinquents, we only ſay it is not proper to him <hi>quarto modo:</hi> For if the King pardon him which hath murthered my ſonne, his pardon ſhall not cut me off from my appeale; and 'tis more unreaſonable, that the Kings pardon ſhould make a whole State, which hath ſuffered, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe, then any private man. So if the King ſhould deny in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity to theſe which in the furie of Warre have done thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtifiable by the Lawes of Peace, and thereby keep the wounds of the State from being bound up, 'tis equitable that an Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33168:31"/>ſhould be made forcible another may. And if this will not hold, yet this is no good conſequence, the King is abſolute in point of pardons, therefore he is abſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e in all things elſe; and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath no power to diſcharge Delinquencies, therefore it hath no power in other matters.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="part">
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <p>The Parliament hath declared the King to be in no condition to govern: but this muſt not be interpreted rigidly, and without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for if the King with his ſword drawn in his hand, and purſuing the Parliament and their adherents as Rebels, be not fit for all Acts of Government, yet 'tis not hereby inſinuated that he is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested of the habit or right of governing: If he be unqualified now, he is not unqualified for the future; if he may not doe things deſtructive to the Parliament, he is not barred from returning to the Parliament, or doing juſtice to the Parliament. This is a fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous cavil, and <hi>ſubturfuge.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="part">
                     <head>7.</head>
                     <p>We ſweare, that the King is our ſupreme Governour over all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and in all Cauſes; but we doe not ſweare that he is above all Law, nor above the ſafety of his people, which is the end of the Law, and indeed <hi>Paramount</hi> to the Law it ſelfe. If he be above all Law, or liable to no reſtraint of our Law, then we are no freer then the <hi>French</hi> or the <hi>Turks;</hi> and if he be above the prime and of Law, <hi>common fafety,</hi> then we are not ſo free as the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Turks:</hi> For if the totall ſubverſion of the <hi>French</hi> or the <hi>Turk</hi> were attempted, they might by Gods Law, imprinted in the Book of Nature, juſtifie a ſelf-defence; but we muſt remedileſty periſh, when the King pleaſes to command our threats. Beſides, how atchieved the King of <hi>England</hi> ſuch a Supremacie above all Law and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity it ſelfe, for whoſe behoofe Law was made? If Gods dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be pleaded, which is not ſpeciall to him, or different from what other Kings may pretend to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, then to what purpoſe ſerve our Laws, nay, to what purpoſe ſerve the Laws of other Countries? for by this generall donation, all Nations are condemned to all ſervitude as well as we. If the Law of this Land be appealed to, what Books hath Mr <hi>Ienkins</hi> read, where hath he found ont that <hi>Lex Regia,</hi> whereby the people of <hi>England</hi> have given away from themſelves all right in themſelves? Some of our Books tell us, that we are more free then the <hi>French;</hi> that the King cannot oppreſſe us in our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33168:32"/>our perſons, or eſtates, by impriſonment, denying juſtice, or laying Taxes without our conſents: other Books tell us, that the ſafety of the people is the ſupreme Law, and that the King hath both God and the Law for his Superiour: But all this is nothing to learned Mr <hi>Ienkins.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="part">
                     <head>8.</head>
                     <p>We admit, that no Acts of Parliament are compleat, or formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binding, without the Kings aſſent: yet this is ſtill to be denyed, that therefore without this aſſent particularly expreſt, the two Houſes can doe nothing, nor have any virtuall power at all, no, not to examine Mr <hi>Ienkins,</hi> nor to doe any other thing of like nature, though in order to publick juſtice and ſafety. I have done, and wiſh Mr <hi>Ienkins</hi> would call in and lick up againe his black infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous execrable reproaches, ſo filthily vomited out againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>To the firſt.</head>
                     <p>I Was examined by a Committee appointed by the Houſe of Commons: I ſay and ſaid that the Houſe of Commons have no power to examine me, for that it is no Court; every Court hath power to examine upon Oath; this power the Houſe of Commons never claimed; The Court of <hi>Pie-powders, Court-Baron, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Court,
<note place="margin">5 H. 4. c. 3. 3 H. 6.46. 1, H 6.43. 35 H. 6.5.</note> County Court,</hi> and every other Court of Record, or not of Record, hath power to examine upon oath; and an exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation without Oath is a communication only; examination in Law is upon Oath.</p>
                     <p>There is no Court without a power of tryall; the Houſe of Commons have no power to try any offence,
<note place="margin">Sir Anthony Maynes caſe, Cook 5. pars, Reports, Lit. 2. lib. Sect. 194.6. H. 4.1.</note> nor ever practiſed it by Bill, Inditement, Information, Plaint or Originall, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it to tryal, nor to try it by Verdict, Demurrer or Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Witneſſes upon Oath, without which there can be no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation or judgement; and that which can attaine to no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable end, the Law rejects as a thing <hi>inutile</hi> and uſeleſſe; <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens incipit a fine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Writ Whereby they are called gives them power <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> faciendum &amp; conſentiendum;</hi> to what? to ſuch things <hi>Que ibidem de communi Conſilie ordinari contigerint,
<note place="margin">4 pars, inſtit. fol. 4. &amp; 9.</note> (viz.)</hi> in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: This makes nothing at all for a Court for the Houſe of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33168:32"/>Commons; that <hi>conſilium</hi> which that Writ intends, is cleared partly by the Writ for chuſing Knights, &amp;c. For the King by that Writ is ſaid to reſolve to conſult and treat with the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Peeres of the Kingdome, for and touching the great concernments of the Common-wealth (for the King never ſits in the Houſe of Commons;) and this alſo is made evident by the Writs to the Prelates, Peeres, Iudges, and to his Councell at Law; the words in their Writ are, <hi>To appear and attend the Parliament, conſilium impenſuri,</hi> the one doth <hi>conſulere,</hi> the other <hi>facere &amp; conſentire.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Houſe of Lords, where the King ſits in perſon,
<note place="margin">7. H. 6.28. 1 H. 7.20. 13. E. 3. ca. 5. 4 pars, inſtit. pag. 21.</note> aſſiſted by his Lords, Judges, Serjeants, Atturney, Sollicitor, Maſters of the Cnancery, is a Court of Record to many purpoſes, ſet down in the Books of Law and the Statutes of the Land, and that Court is only in the Houſe of Lords, where the Kings ſits.</p>
                     <p>A Court muſt either be by the Kings Patent, Statute Law, or by the Common Law, which is common and conſtant uſage; the Houſe of Commons hath no Patent to be a Court,
<note place="margin">Plowd. Com. 319.</note> nor Statute Law to be a Court, nor common uſage; they have no Iournall Book but ſince <hi>E.</hi> 6. time: was there ever Fine by the Houſe of Commons eſtreated into the Exchequer? For murder or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony they can impriſon no man, much leſſe for Treaſon; that Houſe which cannot doe the leſſe, cannot doe the greater.</p>
                     <p>It is ordained,
<note place="margin">25. E. 3. c. 4.3. Car. Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Right.</note> that no man ſhall be impriſoned or put out of his Franchiſe by the King or his Councell, but upon Indictment or preſentment of his good and lawfull Neighbours, where the deed is done, or by originall Writ at the Common Law, and ſo is <hi>Lex terrae</hi> the Law of the land mentioned in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> cap. 29. expounded, and the ſaid <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and <hi>Charta de Foreſta,</hi> are declared by the Stat. of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. to be the Common Law of the Land. All Iudges and Commiſſioners are to proceed, <hi>Secundum legem &amp; conſuetudinem Regni Anglia,</hi> as appeares by all proceedings in all Courts, and by all Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and therefore the Houſe of Commons by themſelves, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding not by Indictment, Preſentment, or Originall Writ, have no power to impriſon men, or put them out of their Franchiſe.</p>
                     <p>This no way trenches upon the Parliament; for it is in Law no Parliament without King and both Houſes;
<note place="margin">4 pars. Inſtit. pag. 1. 3 Pars, Inſtit. p. 23.</note> I have only in my Paper delivered to Mr <hi>Corbet,</hi> applyed my ſelfe to that Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33168:33"/>that they had no power to examine me,
<note place="margin">12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 7.20. Princes caſe, 8 Pars, Cook. 1 Pars, Inſtit. p. 159. 14. H. 8.3. Dier, 38. H. 8.60. 1 Pars, Inſtit. p. 19. b.</note> but I never thought, ſaid, or wrote, that the Parliament had no power to examine me: the Law and cuſtome of this Land is, that a Parliament hath power over my life, liberty, lands and goods, and over every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubject, but the Houſe of Commons of it ſelfe hath no ſuch power.</p>
                     <p>For the Lord <hi>Cooks</hi> relation, that the Houſe of Commons have impoſed Fines, and impriſoned men in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> time, and ſince; Few facts of late time never queſtioned, make no le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall power nor Court;
<note place="margin">4 Pa. Inſtit. ca. Parl.</note> 
                        <hi>à facto ad jus</hi> is no good argument; for the words of the Statute of 6. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 16. that a licence to depart from the Houſe of Commons for any Member thereof is to be entred of Record in the Book of the Clark of the Parliament, appointed, or to be appointed for that Houſe, doth not conclude that the Houſe of Commons is a Court of Record.</p>
                     <p>For firſt, that Law of 6. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 26. handles no ſuch queſtion, as that, whether the Houſe of Commons be a Court; it is a maxime in all Lawes, <hi>Lex aliud tranctans nil probat,</hi> the word <hi>(Record)</hi> there mentioned, is only a memoriall of what was done and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in a Book: A Plaint removed out of the County-Court to the Court of the Common-Pleas, hath theſe words in the Writ of remove,
<note place="margin">Fitzh. Nat. Br. 70. Fitzh. Nat. Br. 13. 12. H 4.23. 34. H. 6.49.</note> 
                        <hi>Recordari facias loquelam, &amp;c.</hi> and yet the County-Court is no Court of Record; and ſo for ancient Demeſne, in a Writ of falſe judgement, the words are <hi>Recordari facias loque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, &amp;c.</hi> and yet the Court of ancient Demeſne is no Court of Reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d; and ſo of a Court Baron, the Law and cuſtome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> muſt be preſerved, or <hi>England</hi> will be deſtroyed, and have neither Law nor cuſtome.</p>
                     <p>Let any man ſhew me, that the Court of Lords or the Houſe of Commons in any age hath made any man a Delinquent <hi>(Rege diſſentiente)</hi> the King contradicting it under his Great Seale. Sir <hi>Giles M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mpeſſau, Michell,</hi> and others of late were condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the proſecution of the Houſe of Commons in King <hi>James</hi> his time; did King <hi>James</hi> ever contradict it? And ſo of ancient times,
<note place="margin">4 Pars, Inſlit. Tit. Parliam. pag. 23.</note> where the Houſe of Peeres condemned the Lord <hi>Latimer</hi> in 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Kings pardon freed him: which ſhewes cleerly, that the Kings expreſſe or implyed aſſent muſt of neceſſity be had to make a Delinquent.</p>
                     <p>The Geatleman ſaith, <hi>That the Parliament ſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, or ought
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33168:33"/>to ſit by ſomething greater th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n the Kings Writ, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>No Parliament did ever ſit without the Kings Writ, nor could ever Parliament begin without the Kings preſence in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<note place="margin">4 Pars, Inſtit. pag. 4. &amp; 6.</note> or by a Guardian of <hi>England</hi> by pacent under the Kings Great Seale, the King being <hi>in re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> or by Commiſſion under the Great Seale to certaine Lords repreſenting the Kings perſon, and it hath been thus in all Ages unto this Seſſion of Parliament, wherein his Majeſty hath been preſſed, and hath paſſed two Acts of Parliament, one for a Triennall Parliament, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a perpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uall, if the Houſes pleaſe, to ſatisfie their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow theſe two Acts agree one with another, and with the Statute in <hi>E.</hi> the thirds time, where Parliaments are ordained to be holden every yeare,
<note place="margin">4 E. 3. c. 14. 36. E. 3. c. 10.21. Iac. the Act of Limitation of Actions, cap. 26.</note> and what miſchiefes to the people of this Land ſuch length of Parliaments will produce by protections and priviledges to free them and their meniall ſervants from all debts during their lives, if they pleaſe to continue it ſo long, and how deſtructive to mens actions againſt them, by reaſon of the Statute of Limitations, which confines their actions to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain years, and many other inconveniences of greater impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, is eaſie to underſtand.</p>
                     <p>How can any man affirm, that the two Houſes doe act now by the Kings Wrie, which relates to Counſell and Treaty with the King, concerning the King, the defence of his Kingdome, and of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">4 Pars, Inſtit. p. 14.</note> theſe are the three points which it tends to, as appeares by the Writ. They keep their King priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at <hi>Holnby,</hi> and will not ſuffer him to conſult and treat with them.
<note place="margin">Vow and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, p. 11.</note> They have made a Vow and Covenant to aſſiſt the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces raiſed and continued by both Houſes againſt the Forces raiſed by the King without their conſent, and to the ſame effect have deviſed the Oath which they call the <hi>Negative Oath:</hi> Is this to to defend the Kings Kingdome or their Kingdome?</p>
                     <p>When by their Solemn League and Covonant they extirpate Biſhops, Deanes and Chapters root and branch, is this to defend the Church of <hi>England?</hi> (that Church muſt neceſſarily be meant, that was the Church of <hi>England</hi> when the ſaid Writ bore teſt) they were not ſummoned to defend a Church that was not in being;
<note place="margin">3 Pars, Cook<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Deane and Chapter of Norwich.</note> to deſtroy and defend the Church are very contrary things; the Church is not deſended, when they take away and ſell the Lands of the Church.</p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33168:34"/>
                     <p>The Gentleman ſaith, <hi>The King cannot contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>le other Courts of Juſtice, or prevent them from ſitting or acting, and therefore not the two Houſes, &amp;c.</hi> It is true, the King cannot controle or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his other Courts, for that they are his ordinary Courts of common Iuſtice, to adminiſter common right unto all men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fixed Lawes.
<note place="margin">14 H. 8.3. 36 H. 8. Dier. 60.</note> The Houſes make no Court without the King, they are no body corporate without the King, nor Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament without the King, they all make one corporate body, one Court called the Parliament,
<note place="margin">4 Pars, Inſtit. pa. 1.</note> whereof the King is the head, and the Court is in the Lords Houſe, where the King is preſent: and as a man is no man without a head, ſo the Houſes ſevered from the King, as now they are, have no power at all, and they themſelves by levying wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> againſt the King, and impriſoning of him, have made the Statute for not diſſolving, adjourning, or proroging this Parliament of no effect, by the ſaid Acts of their own; they ſit to no purpoſe without his aſſent to their Bills, they will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to conſult with them, and treat, and reaſon with them; whereby he may diſcern what Bills are fit to paſſe, and what not, which in all Ages the Kings of this Land have enjoyed as their undoubted Rights, and therefore they ſit to no purpoſe by their own diſobedience and fault.</p>
                     <p>For the ordinary Courts at <hi>Westminſter,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">27 H. 8. c. 24. 28 H. 8.11. Dier.</note> the Iudges in all thoſe Courts are Iudges by the Kings Patent or Writ, otherwiſe they are no Iudge: the Houſes can make no Iudges, they are no Iudges at all who are made by them; the whole &amp; ſole power of making Iudges, belongs to the King: the King cannot controule or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his own Iudges from ſitting or acting, but the Houſes hee may, for they are not the Kings Iudges, but the Iudges of the two Houſes.
<note place="margin">2 R. 3.11.</note> In his other Courts, the King commits his power to his Iudges by his Patent, and they are ſworn to doe common right to all men, and the King is ſworn not to let them from ſo doing: the King cannot judge in thoſe Courts, nor controule; but the King is both Iudge and Controller in the Court of Parliament: <hi>Quoad</hi> Acts, for his aſſent or diſſent doth give life or death to all Bills. Many Lawyers have much to anſwer to God, this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſterity, for puzling the poore of this Land with ſuch Fancies, as the Gentleman who wrote the Anſwer to my Paper, and others have publiſhed in theſe Troubles, which hath been none of the leaſt cauſes of the rayſing and continuing of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33168:34"/>them: And ſo I have with the firſt part of his Anſwer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>AD. 2.</head>
                     <p>For the <hi>Non ſequitur,</hi> in the ſecond Section of the Gent. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the Antecedent and the Cenſequent are his own.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Quem recitas meus eſt (ô Fidentine!) libellus:</l>
                        <l>Sed malè dum recitas incipit eſſe tuus.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>My words are, that the King is not virtually in the two Houſes at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to enable them to grant pardons, for that whole and ſole power by the Law belongs to the King. My Paper hath no ſuch thing,
<note place="margin">27 H. 8. c. 24.</note> as that the Kings power cannot be derived to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or the vertue of his power: For his power, and the vertue of his power, is in all Patents to his Iudges, in Charters to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, in Commiſſions of all ſorts, and in the Parliament aſſembled by force of his Writ of Summons, ſo long as they obey him; but when they renounce that power, and claime it not from the King, and declare to the Kingdome that he is not in condition to govern, and impriſon him, and uſurp to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all Royall Authority, as the two Houſes now doe, no reaſonable man can affirm that they act by the power of their priſoner, who hath no power to give them, that by force of Armes take all the power to themſelves.</p>
                     <p>The Gent. ſaith, the <hi>King grants Commiſſions daily of</hi> Oyer <hi>and</hi> Terminer, <hi>which he cannot fruſtrate nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lude.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">4 E. 4.39. 5 F. 4.4. 1 Eliz, Dyer 165. 1 Mar. Brooks caſe, 447.</note> The King may revoke and diſcharge the Commiſſion by his Writ, as he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all Iudges, and place other men in their roome; and any Kings death determines all the Iudges Patents of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, Commiſſions of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo he might diſſolve both Houſes in all times, by his Writ under the Great Seale, untill that by this Parliament, by his own conceſſion, the King of his goodneſſe hath ſecluded himſelf; which goodneſſe hath been full ill requited.</p>
                     <p>The Gent, affirms, <hi>That the power the Parliament hath, is concurrent from the King and Kingdome;</hi> which, he conceives, is proved by the Grant of Subſidies to the King by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The miſtaking of this word <hi>(Parliament)</hi> hath been miſchievous in theſe times to this Land,
<note place="margin">4 Pars, Inſtit. pag 1.</note> and it is affectedly miſtaken, which makes the ſinne the greater, for the two Houſes are not the Parliament, as before is declared; and at this time ſo to inculcate it, when all men know, that of the 120 Peeres of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33168:35"/>Kingdome, who were Temporal Peeres before the Troubles; there are not now above 30 in the Lords Houſe, and in the Houſe of Commons about 200 of the principall Gent. of the Kingdome left the Houſe, and adhered to his Majeſty, who is impriſoned by them, ſhewes no ſuch candor as is to be deſired.</p>
                     <p>It is true, that no Tallage can be layd upon the people of this Land,
<note place="margin">25. E. 1. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatio char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum, cap. 6. 34. E. 1. cap. 1. de Tallagio non conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo.</note> but by their conſent in Parliament, as appeareth by the Lawes mentioned in the Margent; but you ſhall finde in Mr <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ns</hi> learned Book, called <hi>Mare Clauſum,</hi> a number of Preſidents in <hi>Henry</hi> the Thirds time for Ship-money, juſtly condemned this Parliament, to the which his Majeſty aſſented; and in truth, that Ship-money was condemned before, by the ſaid two Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. &amp; 34. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>de Tallagio non concedendo. Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelt, Englitery,</hi> and many grievous burthens were laid upon the people, and born, untill that memorable Princes time. But I am of opinion, that the Common Law of the Land did alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine Kings form all Subſidies and Tallages, but by conſent in Parliament; which doth appear by <hi>Magna Charta</hi> the laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where the Prelates, Lords, and Communalty gave the King the fifteenth part of their moveables. In truth it is no manner of conſequence, becauſe the King cannot take what he pleaſeth of the ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ects goods, that therefore they have a concurrent power in Parliament: there have been many Parliaments, and no Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies granted; Parliaments may be without Subſidies, but Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies cannot be without Parliaments: of ancient time Parliaments rarely granted any, unleſſe it were in the time of forraine Warres; and in my time, Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> refuſed a Subſidy granted in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and in the Parliament of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Jac.</hi> none were granted. The Gent. ſhould make a conſcience of blinding the people with ſuch untrue colours, to the ruine of King and people.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>AD. 3.</head>
                     <p>The Gent. affirms, <hi>That the ſonding Propoſitions to the King, and deſiring his concurrence, is carce worth an anſwer, for Sub, ects may humbly petition for that which is their ſtrict right and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c.</hi> The Propoſitions ſent to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> are in print; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the two Houſes are ſo farre from humbly petitioning, that they ſtile not themſelves his Majeſties Subjects, as appeares by the Propoſitions.</p>
                     <p>That they have a ſtrict right or property to any one of theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33168:35"/>Propoſitions, is a ſtrange aſſertion, every one of them being againſt the Lawes now in force: Have the two Houſes a ſtrict right and property, to lay upon the people what Taxes they ſhall judge meet? To pardon all Treaſons, &amp;c. that is one of their Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. Have they a ſtrict right and proporty to pardon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? and ſo for all the reſt of their Propoſitions.</p>
                     <p>Theſe Propoſitions have been Voted by both Houſes,
<note place="margin">12 H. 7.20. 1 Iac. cap. 1. 1 Car. cap. 7.</note> the Kings aſſent (the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> being drawn into Bills) makes them Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Hath the King no right to aſſent or diſ-aſſent? Was the ſending but a Complement? All our Law-Books and Statutes ſpeak otherwiſe. This Gent. and others, muſt give an account one time or other for ſuch deluſions put upon the people.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <head>AD. 4.</head>
                     <p>The Gent. ſaith, <hi>They affirm not, that the Kings power is ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from his perſon, ſo as the two</hi> Spencers <hi>affirmed, &amp;c.</hi> His Majeſties perſon is now at <hi>Holnby</hi> under their Guards; have they not ſevered his power from him, when by no power they have left him, he can have two of his Chaplaines, who have not taken their Covenant, to attend him for the exerciſe of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</p>
                     <p>For the three Concluſions of the <hi>Spencers,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">15. Ed. 2. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilium Hugonis 1 E. 3. c. 2. Calvins caſe. 7 Pars, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, 11.</note> doe not the two Houſes act every of them? They ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, his Majeſty hath broken his Truſt, touching the Government of his people: They have raiſed Armies to take him, they have taken him, and impriſoned him; they govern themſelves; they make Lawes, impoſe Taxes, make Iudges, Sheriffes, and take upon them <hi>omnia inſigna ſummae p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>statis:</hi> Is not this to remove the King for miſdemeanours, to reform <hi>per aspertè,</hi> to govern in aide of him; the three Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>Pencers?</hi> Doe they think the good people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are become ſtupid, and will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t length ſee theſe things?</p>
                     <p>The Gentleman ſaith, <hi>They doe not ſeparate his power from his Perſon, but diſtinguiſh it, &amp;c.</hi> His power is in his legall Writs,
<note place="margin">Plowd. 4. Eliz. 213. the Kings power and his Perſon are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſible.</note> Courts, and Officers: when they counterfeit the Great Seale, and ſeale Writs with the ſame, make Iudges themſelves, Courts and Officers, by their own Ordinances againſt his conſent, declared under his true Great Seale of <hi>England</hi> (not by word of mouth, letters, or miniſters only) their Seale is obeyed, their own Writs, their own Iudges, their own Courts, their own Officers, and not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33168:36"/>the Kings: The time will come when ſuch ſtrange actions and diſcourſes will be lamented.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="part">
                     <head>AD. 5.</head>
                     <p>The Gentleman goes on, <hi>We take not from the King all power of pardoning Delinquents, we only ſay it is not proper to him</hi> quarto modo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What doe you meane by <hi>quarto modo?</hi> I am ſure, <hi>Omnis Rex Angliae, ſolus Rex &amp; ſemper Rex</hi> can doe it, and none elſe; read the Books of the Law to this purpoſe collected by that reverend and learned Iudge <hi>Stanford,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Stanfor. Plcas 99. 27 H 8. c. 24. Dier, 163.</note> from all Antiquity to his time, who dyed in the laſt year of King <hi>Philip</hi> and Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Reign, you ſhall finde this a truth undeniable; and this power was never queſtioned in any Age in any Book by any untill this time, that every thing is put to the queſtion: You Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who profeſſe the Law, and maintaine the party againſt the King, return at length, and bring not ſo much ſcandall upon the Law, (which preſerves all) by publiſhing ſuch incredible things.</p>
                     <p>We hold only what the Law holds, the Kings Prerogative and the Subjects Liberty are determined, and bounded, and admea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the written Law what they are;
<note place="margin">1 Pars, Inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t. pag. 344. Plowd. 3. Eliz. 236, 237.</note> we doe not hold the King to have any more power, neither doth His Majeſty claime any other but what the Law gives him; the two Houſes by the Law of this Land have no colour of power, either to make De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, or pardon Delinquents, the King contradicting: (and the Army under Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> (howbeit but Souldiers) doe now underſtand that to be Law, and doe now evidently ſee and aſſuredly know, that it is not an Ordinance of the two Houſes, but an act of Parliament, made by the King, Lords and Commons that will ſecure them, and let this Army remember their executed fellow Souldiers,) And the Law was alwayes ſo taken by all men untill theſe troubles, that have begot Monſters of opinions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="part">
                     <head>AD. 6.</head>
                     <p>This Gentleman ſayes, <hi>The Parliament hath declared the King to be in no condition to govern, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is no end of your diſtinctions, I and you profeſſe the Law; ſhew me Law for your diſtinctions, or letter, ſyllable, or line, in any Age in the Books of the Law, that the King may in one time be in no condition to govern, and yet have the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33168:36"/>of governing, and another time he may <hi>(viz.)</hi> when the two Houſes will ſuffer him: The Law ſaith thus, <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi lex non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguit, non eſt diſtinguendum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſayes, <hi>The King is not barred from returning to His Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> (as he calls the two Houſes) he knowes the contrary, the whole City knowes the contrary, <hi>Nos juris conſulti ſumus ſacerdotes, (as Inſtitian</hi> the Emperour hath it, in the firſt Book of his <hi>Inſtitutions</hi>) and therefore knowledge and truth ſhould come from our lips: Worth) and ingenious men will remember, and reflect upon that paſſage of that good and wiſe man <hi>Seneca, Non qua itur, ſed qua eundum;</hi> follow not the rayes of the Lawyers of the Houſe of Commons: God forgive them, I am ſure the King will, if they be wiſe and ſeek it in time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="part">
                     <head>AD. 7.</head>
                     <p>The Gent. ſayes, <hi>We ſweare that the King is our ſupreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour over all perſons and in all cauſes, &amp;c.</hi> Why hath he leſt out the word <hi>(only)?</hi> for the oath the Members now take, is, that King <hi>Charles</hi> is now the only and ſupreme Governour in all cauſes, over all perſons,
<note place="margin">5 El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>z. cap. 1. Cawdreys caſe 5 pars, fol. 1.</note> and yet they keep their only Supreme Governour now in priſon, and act now in Parliament by vertue of their Priſoners Writ, and by a concurrent power in this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and by their own ſtrict right and property, (as the Gent.
<note place="margin">This Oath is allowed by the Common L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>w of the Land</note> affirms in his Anſwer) Theſe things agree well with their Oath, that the King is the only Supreme Governour in all cauſes, over all perſons; this Oath is taken now in the Parliament time, by all the Members of the Houſe of Commons, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the Law to be taken in all Parliaments, otherwiſe they have no power, nor colour to meddle with the publike Affaires.</p>
                     <p>This Oath being taken in Parliament, that <hi>the King is the only and Supreme Governour in all Cauſes,</hi> then it followes in Parliament cauſes; <hi>over all perſons,</hi> then over the two Houſes; let them keep this Oath; and we ſhall be ſure of peace in the Land: and good Lawyers ought to deſire peace, both for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir private, and not diſhonour that Noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as many doe in this miſerable time.</p>
                     <p>The Gent. ſayes, <hi>We doe not ſweare that the King i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> above all Law nor above the ſafety of his people;</hi> neither doe we ſo ſweare, but His Majeſty and we will ſweare to the contrary, and have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33168:37"/>ſwom, and have made good, and will by Gods grace make good our Oath to the world, that the King is not above the Law, nor above the ſafety of his people; the Law and the ſafery of his people are his ſafety, his Honour and his Strength.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="part">
                     <p>AD. 8.</p>
                     <p>The Gent. concludes, <hi>That Acts of Parliament are not formally binding, nor compleat without the Kings aſſent, yet the Houſes have a virtuall power without the Kings particular aſſent, to doe things in order to publike Iustice and Safety, (viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</hi> In ſetting up the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, in raiſing and maintaining of Armies, in taxing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people at pleaſure with Fifth and Twentieth part, Fifty Subſidies, Sequeſtrations, Loanes, Compoſitions, impriſoning the King, aboliſhing the Common-prayer-Book, ſelling the Churches Lands &amp;c. all theſe are in order to the publike Juſtice and Safety.</p>
                     <p>Mr <hi>H.P.</hi> you are of my profeſſion, I beſeech you, for the good of your Countrey, for the Honour of our Science perſwade your ſelfe and others, as much as in you lies, to believe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the monition and Councell of that memorable, reverend, and profoundly learned in the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the Land, the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> who writes as becomes a great and a learned Judge of the Law (a perſon much magnified by the two Houſes) in theſe words? <hi>Peruſe over all Books, Records and Histories, and you ſhall finds a Principle in Law,
<note place="margin">3 Pars, Inſtit. p. 36.</note> a Rule in Reaſon, and a Tryall in Experience, that Treaſon doth over produc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> futall and finall deſtruction to the offender, and never attaines to the deſired and (two incidents inſeparable thereunto) and therefore l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t all men abandon it, as the poyſonous hait of the Devill, and follow the Precept in holy Scripture, SERVE GOD, HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R THE KING, AND HAVE NO COMPANY WITH THE SEDITIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
                     <p>I <hi>Say againe, that without an Act of Obliviow, a gracious generall Pardon from His Majeſty, the Arreares of the Soulaiers paid, a favorable regard had to tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there will be neither Truth nor Peace in this Land, nor any man ſecure of any thing be hath:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>By me <hi>David Jenkins</hi> Priſoner in the Tower.</signed>
                     </closer>
                     <trailer>The End.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A DISCOURSE Touching the Inconveniencies of a Long continued Parliament. AND THE IVDGEMENT OF THE LAW OF THE LAND In that Behalfe.</p>
                  <p>By DAVID JENKINS now Priſoner in the Tower of LONDON.</p>
                  <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:38"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33168:38"/>
                  <head>A DISCOURSE Touching the Inconveniencies of a Long continued Parliament.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <p>Aerpetuall Parliament is repugnant to the Act made this Parliament for a Trienniall Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for how can every three years a Parliament begin, if this be perpetuall, which may be ſo if the two Houſes pleaſe?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <p>An adjournment of the Parliament makes no Seſſion, 4 <hi>Pars, Inſtitut. fol.</hi> 27. Howbeit, before the Adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the King gives His Royall aſſent to ſome Bills. <hi>Cooke, ibid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <p>There is no Seſſion till a prorogation or diſſolution of the Parliament.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <p>This Parliament, as appeares by the Act for not diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereof, ſet downe in the Printed Statutes of this Parliament, <hi>fol.</hi> 138. cannot be prorogued but by Act of Parliament. There hath beene as yet no Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſent, and therefore all the Acts of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are Acts of one Seſſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="part">
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:33168:39"/>
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <p>All the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> of one Seſſion relate to the firſt day of the Parliament,
<note place="margin">Plow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> com. 79 35 H. 8. Bro. relation 35. Bro. Parl. 86. Dier. 1 Mariae 45.</note> and all the Acts of ſuch a Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>liament are Acts of one day; ſo the Act for the Trienniall, and the Act for this Perpetuall, are two Acts of one day by the Law.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="part">
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <p>4 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> and 36 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. A Parliament is to bee holden once every yeere, and more often if need<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall bee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thoſe Acts are confirmed by the Act for the Trienniall Parliament. How doth a perpetuall Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment agree with a Parliament once every yeere, or with the intention of thoſe Lawes? How doth a Parliament every three yeers agree with a Parliament for ever, which may be, if the two Houſes pleaſe?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="part">
                     <head>7.</head>
                     <p>The reſult is this; at one day in Law this Parliament two Acts have paſſed (for howbeit the one was in 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Carol.</hi> and the other in 17. <hi>Carol.</hi> yet both in Law are Acts of one day) the one ſaith there ſhall be a Trienniall Parliament after the end of the ſitting of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: The other, this Parliament ſhall ſit for ever, if they pleaſe. The one will have a Parliament with an end, the other, a Parliament without an end.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>When an Act of Parliament is againſt common right or Reaſon,
<note place="margin">8 Pars, Doct. Bonhams caſe fol. 118. 8 Ed. 3.30. 33 E. 3. ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, 32. 27. H. G. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity 11. 14 Eliz. Dier, 313.</note> or repugnant, or impoſſible to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the Common Law ſhall controle it, and adjudge this Act to bee void; they are the words of the Law.</p>
                     <p>An Act of Parliament, that a man ſhall bee Judge in his owne cauſe, is a void Act.</p>
                     <p>Begin with Common Right. It is againſt Common Right, that indebted men ſhould not pay their debts: That if any Member of the Houſe of Comons doe any Subject wrong by diffeiſing him of his land, or diſpoſſeſſing him of his goods, or blaſting of his fame, or doing violence to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33168:39"/>his perſon, that ſuch perſons during their lives ſhould not bee queſtioned by a priviledge of Parliament, and that extended alſo to many others beſides themſelves. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Right doth abhorre theſe enormities, which a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Paliament doth beget, beſides the utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all mens actions, reall, perſonall, or mixt, who have to doe with Parliament men,
<note place="margin">21 Jac.</note> by the Statute of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, which confines ſuits to certain yeares.</p>
                     <p>For Common Reaſon. Parliaments were ordained for remedies to redreſſe publike grievances; It is againſt Reaſon they ſhould make publike and inſufferable grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. The Law of the Land allowes no protection for any man imployed in the ſervice of the Kingdome but for a yeare, to be free from ſuits, and in many ſuits none at all, howbeit hee be in ſuch ſervice;
<note place="margin">39 H. 6.39.</note> but a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment perpetuall may prove a protection, not for a yeare, but for ever, which is againſt all manner of Reaſon.</p>
                     <p>For Impoſſibility. The death of His Majeſty (whoſe life God prolong) diſſolves it neceſſarily; For the Writ of ſummons is, <hi>Carolus Rex in hoc individuo,</hi> and <hi>Carolus Rex</hi> is in this particular, <hi>Habiturus colloquium &amp; tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum cum Prelatis &amp; proceribus, &amp;c.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 H. 5. Cooke Title Parliam 3. pars.</note> King <hi>Charles</hi> being to have Conference and Treaty with his Prelates and Peeres; <hi>Carolus Rex</hi> cannot have <hi>Colloquium &amp; tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> Conference and Treaty, when he is deceaſed; and therefore it is impoſſible for any Parliament to continue as long as they pleaſe, as for a Parliament to make a dead man alive.</p>
                     <p>For Repugnancie. That which is but for a time, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be affirmed to have continuance for ever, it is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
                     <p>The end of the Act of 17. <hi>Caroli Regis,</hi> which is to continue at pleaſure, is in the ſaid Act expreſſed to be to raiſe credit for money for theſe three purpoſes. Firſt, for reliefe of his Majeſties Army and people in the North.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33168:40"/>Secondly, for preventing the iminent danger of the Kingdome. Thirdly, for ſupply of other His Majeſties preſent and urgent occaſions. Theſe ends are ended, the reliefe of that Army, the iminent danger ſuppoſed was ſixe yeares agoe, the ſupply of His Majeſtie hath beene a ſupply againſt him, take away the end, the meanes thereto are to no purpoſe, take away the cauſe, the effect ceaſeth; and therefore the three ends of this Act being determined, it agreeth with Law and Reaſon, the Act ſhould end,
<note place="margin">Sir Anthony Mayns caſe. 5. pars, 1. H. 4.6. Littl. cap. Villen.</note> the Law rejects things unprofitable and uſeleſſe.</p>
                     <p>A perpetuall Parliament (beſides that it incites men to ſelfe-ends, deſtructive of the publique of which the whole Kingdome hath had ſufficient experience) wilbe a conſtant charge to the Kingdome; for that every County and Borough, who ſend Members to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, are by the Law to pay wages to their Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment men, which to many Counties will amount above ſome Subſidies Yearely: There are many poore Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough-Townes in each County of this Kingdome, who being to maintaine two Burgeſſes in Parliament, will be quickly begger'd, if the Parliament have no end; for all which reaſons it is cleare, that ſuch long continuance of Parliaments, will inſtead of a remedy (which is and ought to be the proper and true end of Parliaments) become an inſufferable grievance and oppreſſion to all the People of the Land.</p>
                     <p>The Writ of Summons this Parliament is the baſis and foundation of the Parliament. If the Foundation be deſtroyed the Parliament falls. The Aſſembly of Parliament if for three purpoſes. <hi>Rex eſt habiturus collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium et tractatum cum praelatis, magnatibus et proceribus ſuper arduis negotijs, concernentibus,</hi> 1. Nos. 2 <hi>Defenſionem regni noſtri</hi> 3. <hi>Defenſionem Eccleſiae Anglicanae.</hi> This Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath overthrowne this Foundation in all 3 parts, 1. <hi>Nos.</hi> the King, they have chaſed him away, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33168:40"/>him; they have voted no prelats, and a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other Lords, about 40. in the City muſt not come to the Houſe, and about 40, more are out of Towne, the <hi>colloquium et tractatus</hi> are made void therby. For the King cannot conſult and treat there with men removed from thence. 2. <hi>Defenſionem regni noſtri,</hi> that is gone; they have made it their Kingdome, not His, for they have uſurped all His Soveraigntie. 3. <hi>Defenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Eccleſiae Anglicanae,</hi> that is gone, that <hi>Eccleſia An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicana</hi> truſt be underſtood neceſſarily that Church, that at the teſt of the Writ was <hi>Eccleſia Anglicana,</hi> they have deſtroyed that too. So now theſe men would be called a Parliament, having abated, quaſhed, and made nothing of the Writ whereby they were Summoned and Aſſembled. If the Writ be made void, all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is void alſo: that Houſe muſt needs fall, where the Foundation is overthrowne, <hi>Sublato fundamento opus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> the Foundation being taken away, the worke falls, is both a maxime in Law and Reaſon.</p>
                     <p>For ſome yeares paſt, there is no crime from Treaſon to Treſpaſſe, but they are guilty of: all Treaſon, Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Robberies, treſpaſſes are <hi>contra pacem, coronam, et dignitatem Regis,</hi> againſt the Peace, Crowne and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the King; as appeares by all Indictments in all Ages. <hi>Pax Regis</hi> the Kings Peace, <hi>Corona Regis,</hi> the Kings Crowne, <hi>Dignitas Regis,</hi> the Kings Dignitie, are all trod under foot, and made nothing; <hi>Pax Regis,</hi> the Peace of the King is become a Warre againſt the King, His Dignitie put into priſon, and the Crowne put upon their owne heads.</p>
                     <p>All the Judges of <hi>England</hi> have reſolved,
<note place="margin">Nevills eaſe 7. part, 34. 2. Jacobi.</note> that Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men committing Treaſon have forfeited their Office and Dignitie, their Officei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s to councell the King in time of Peace, to defend him in time of Warre, and therefore thoſe men againſt the duty and end of their Dignitie taking not onely Councell, but Armes alſo to deſtroy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33168:41"/>Him, and being thereof attaint by due courſe of Law by a racite condition annexed to the eſtate of their Dignitie, have forfeited the ſame; they are the words of the Law, and therefore they have made themſelves inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to be Members of the upper Houſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Oppreſſions of the People.</head>
                     <p>Briberies, Extortions, Monopolies, ought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after by the Houſe of Commons, and complained of to the King and Lords, what have they done?</p>
                     <p>The Houſe of Commons cannot by the Law commit any man to priſon, who is not of the ſaid Houſe, for Treaſon, Murder, or Felony, or any thing but for the diſturbance of the publique Peace, by the priviledge of the whole body.</p>
                     <p>They have no power by the Writ, which the King iſſueth to elect and returne Members of that Houſe, ſo to doe. For the Writ for them is onely <hi>ad faciendum et conſentiendum</hi> to thoſe things, whereof His Majeſtie ſhall conſult and treat with his Prelates and Nobles, <hi>et de communi conſilio Regni</hi> ſhall be there ordained, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the Writ. Here is no ſeparate power given over the Kings people to them, but onely <hi>ad faciendum et conſentiendum,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">4 Pars. inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. 23.24.25.</note> and in all times this hath beene expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and reſtrained to that which concerned their owne Members in Relation to the publique Service, as he is a Member of the corporate body of the Parliament, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the King is the Head.</p>
                     <p>But that the Houſe of Commons have committed any man for Treaſon, Murder or Felony, or for any offence that had no relation to a Member of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as it is againſt Law and Reaſon, ſo no inſtance can be given till this Parliament.
<note place="margin">19 H. 6.43. 22. E. 4.22. 5 H. 4. cap. 8. 3 H. 6.46.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>All Queſtions and trials where witneſſe are examined, the examination is upon oath by the Law, by all our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33168:41"/>Bookes, Statutes, every dayes practice. Examination without an Oath, is but a looſe diſcourſe; therefore the Houſe of Commons not claiming power to give an Oath, have no power to examine any man.</p>
                     <p>No man ſhall bee impriſoned by the King or His Councell, unleſſe it be by Inditement,
<note place="margin">25 E. 3. c. 1. Petition of Right. 3 Car.</note> preſentment of his good and lawfull Neighbours where ſuch deeds bee done, in due manner, or by proceſſe made by Writ ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall at the Common Law: This Statute rehearſes <hi>Magna Charta, pag.</hi> 29. and expounds <hi>Lex terrae,</hi> the Law of the Land there mentioned: This Law binds all men, and the Houſe of Commons (for they ſay they are of the Kings Councell) in all points, but onely againſt the diſturbers of the ſervice of the Parliament; and therefore the impriſonment of ſeverall perſons who are not their Members, and for no diſturbance to their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, is utterly againſt the Law of the Land, and the fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe of the Free-men of this Realme.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cui non licet quod minus, non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eet quod majus;</hi> he who may not doe what is leſſe, may not doe what is greater; they cannot commit a man for murder or Felony, much leſſe for Treaſon.</p>
                     <p>No Court can fine and impriſon, but a Court of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, the Houſe of Commons is no Court of Record,
<note place="margin">8 Pars, Cook 120. 27 H. 6.8.</note> the Houſe of the Lords where the King is in his Perſon, his Nobles and his Judges, and Councell at Law, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Chancery aſſiſting, is a Court of Record, and that is the Court of Parliament, where the <hi>colloquium &amp; tractatus</hi> is. The Houſe of Commons may preſent grievances, grant or not grant aydes, conſent or not conſent to new lawes, but for fining and impriſoning any but as aforeſaid, is but of a late date, and no ancient u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: They have no Journall Booke, but ſithence <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. time. 6 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. doth not prove the Houſe of Commons to be a Court of Record, it mentions onely to be entered on Record in the Booke of the Clerke of the Parliament, if any Member depart into the Country.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33168:42"/>There is no Journall there but ſithence <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. time, or it is a remembrance or memoriall, as 12 <hi>H.</hi> 4.23.</p>
                     <p>The whole Parliament is one corporate body,
<note place="margin">14 H. 8.3. 36 H. 8. Dier 60. 4 Pars Inſtit. cap. 1.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the Head and three Eſtates: The Court is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there where the <hi>Conſilium &amp; tractatus</hi> is, where the conſult and treaty is with the King, which is in the Houſe of Lords onely.</p>
                     <p>The Houſe of Commons claime not to examine upon oath any man; no Court can bee without a power to give an oath, Courts Baron, Court of Pipowders, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Court, may and doe give oath: No Court can bee without a power to try, no tryall can be without Oath; and therefore the Houſe of Commons not claiming po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to give an Oath, can bring no matter to tryall, and conſequently can be no Court.</p>
                     <p>The behaviour of the Commons at a Conference with the Lords, the Commons are alwayes uncovered, and ſtanding when the Lords ſit with their hats on, which ſhewes they are not Colleagues in judgement, for fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Judges owe no ſuch Reverence to their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
                     <p>When was ever Fine impoſed by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons eſtreated in the Exchequer?
<note place="margin">11 H. 4. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> The ejecting of a Member, who hath ſitten, is againſt the Law; for they cannot remove a man out of the Houſe unduly returned, much leſſe a man returned duely.</p>
                     <p>By theſe Lawes it appeares,
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> H. 4. cap. 1. 1 H. 5. cap. 1. 8 H. 6. cap. 7. 23 H. 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 15</note> that if any undue returne be made, the perſon returned is to continue a Member, the Sheriffes puniſhment is 200. pound, one to the King, another to the party that is duly elected, impriſonment for a yeare without Baile or Mainpriſe; and that perſon who is unduly returned, ſhall ſerve at his owne charge, and have no benefit at the end of the Parliament by the Writ <hi>De ſolutione foendorum Militum, Civium &amp; Burgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium Parliament.</hi> and the tryall of the falſity of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, is to be before the Juſtices of Aſſiſes in the proper
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33168:42"/>County, or by action of debt in any Court of Record. This condemnes the Committee for undue elections, which hath been practiſed but of late times;
<note place="margin">3 Ed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 20. 5 Ed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 41.</note> for beſides theſe Lawes, it is againſt a maxime of the Common law; an averment is not receivable againſt the returne of the Sheriffe, for his returne is upon Oath, which Oath is to be credited in that ſuit wherein the returne is made.</p>
                     <p>The ſaid Statutes condemne and make thoſe members no members, which were not reſiant in the County or Boroughs, for which they were elected, at the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the reſt of the Writ of the Summons of the Parliament, and any abuſive practice of late times to the contrary is againſt the <hi>Law,</hi> and ought not to be allowed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Aſſault upon Parliament Men.</head>
                     <p>If a Parliament man or his Meniall Servant be aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, beaten, or wounded, in the Parliament time,
<note place="margin">5 H. 4. cap 6. 11 H. 6, cap 11.</note> procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſhall bee made where the deed is done, that the offender ſhall render himſelfe to the Kings Bench, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a quarter of a yeare after proclamation made, and the offence there to be tryed, for default of appearance the offender is declared, attainted of the miſdeed, and it is accorded that thereafter it bee done likewiſe in the like Caſe.</p>
                     <p>Serving of proceſſe upon a Lord of the Parliament pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the Lords Houſe.
<note place="margin">Bogo de Clare 18 E. 3. 4 pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s, Inſtit. fol. 24. Iohn Thornſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes caſe, Clerk of the Parliam. ibid. 10. E. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Serving of proceſſe upon <hi>Thornsby</hi> inquired of in the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and there the offenders were convicted.</p>
                     <p>The premiſſes prove, that breaches of priviledge of Parliament may bee puniſhed elſewhere then in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                     <p>Upon all this Diſcourſe, it is eaſie to diſcerne what fruits may be expected from this Parliament, continuing as long as the two Houſes pleaſe; and that there is no ſafety for this Common-wealth, but by the Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their ancient Franchiſes, Cuſtomes and Lawes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33168:43"/>
                     <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
                     <p>I <hi>Say againe, that without an Act of Oblivion, a gracious generall Pardon from His Majesty, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares of the Souldiers paid, a favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable regard had to tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there will bee neither Truth nor Peace in this Land, nor any man ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of any thing he hath.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <trailer>The End.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE ARMY, Touching the eight Quaeres upon the late Declarations and Letters from the Army, touching ſedition falſly charged upon them.</p>
                  <p>Wherein thoſe Quaeres are reſolved, and thereby the preſent proceedings of the Army are proved to be Legall, Juſt &amp; Honorable.</p>
                  <p>By DAVID JENKINS, Priſoner in the Tower of LONDON.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quis tulerit</hi> Gracchos <hi>de ſeditione querentes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="apology">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33168:44"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33168:44"/>
                  <head>AN APOLOGIE FOR THE ARMY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Treaſonable and inſolent <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> make the Army the Houſes Subjects,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bracton fol.</hi> 118, <hi>Stanford. f.</hi> 2</note> and not the Kings. None by the Lawes of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and can in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome have any Army but His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>It appeares, the Army doth now evidently perceive, that they were miſ-led by the ſpecious pretencees of <hi>Sulus Papuli,</hi> the maintenance of the Kings Honour, and of the maintenance of the Lawes of the Land, and liberties of the Subject, to take up Armes againſt their naturall Liege Lord and Soveraigne, the King. The People is the Body,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mag. Char. c.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; ultim.</hi> All the act concerning the King, Church, and Churchmen. 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> the King is their Head; was the Body ſufe when the Head was diſtreſſed and impriſoned? For Lawes and Liberties have not the prevailing pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tie in the two Houſes deſtroyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 100 Acte of Parliament, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Magun Charta, &amp; Chorta de Foreſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> which are the common Lawes of the Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doth Excize, Fifth and Twentieth Parts, Meale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33168:45"/>and many more burdens which this Land never heard of before maintaine the Liberties of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: You, and that partie of the two Houſes, made the Army by ſeverall. Declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tions before ingagement, believe that you would preſerve the Kings Honour and Greatneſſe, the Lawes and Liberties of the people: The Army and the whole Kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> ſee your actions, and have no reaſon longer to bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eve your Oaths, Vowes, and Declarations; and fince that partie in the two Houſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to performe any thing according to their ſaid Oathes, Vowes, and Declarations. The Army and the Kingdome may and ought, both by your own principles and the Lawes of the Land, purſue the end for which they were rayſed. And ſo your firſt <hi>Quaere</hi> is reſolved, whereby it is manifeſt, that ſpecious pretences to carry on ambitious and pernicious deſignes, fix not upon the Army, but upon you, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing partie in both Houſes.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Solution of the ſecond Quaere.</head>
                     <p>The Army,
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>3. <hi>par. Inſtit. f.</hi> 12.39. <hi>Eli.</hi> 1. <hi>Iacob. ibi.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> to their eternall honour, have freed the King from impriſonment a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Holmby.</hi> It was High Treaſon to impriſon His Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſtie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Tof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> His Majeſtie from that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment was to delive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Him out of Traitero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s mands, which was the Armies bounden dutie by the Law of God and the Land. That partie refuſed to ſuffer His Majeſtie to have two of His Chaplaines for the exerciſe of His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience who had not taken the Covenant, free aceeſſe wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not permitted, doth the Army uſe His Majeſtie ſo all men ſee that acceſſe to Him is free,
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> and ſuch Chaplaines as His Majeſtie deſired are now attending on His Grace: Who are the guiltie perſons, the Army, who in this action of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering the King act according to Law, or the ſaid partie who acted Treaſonably againſt the Law? Who doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Proteſtation better, they who impriſon their King, or they who free Him from priſon?</p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33168:45"/>
                     <p>That this Army was rayſed by the Parliament is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> falſe: The Army was rayſed by the two Houſes upon the ſpecious pretences of the Kings Honour, common ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the preſervation of Lawes and Liberties, which how made good hath beene ſhewed before, and all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Kingdome doe find by wofull experience.</p>
                     <p>The two Houſes are no more a Parliament then a Body without a Head a man.
<note place="margin">14. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 36. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Dier.</hi> 60. 4. <hi>par. Inſtit. p.</hi> 1.3.12.14. 16. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Carol.</hi> The act for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Parliament.</note> The two Houſes can make no Court without the King, they are no Body Corporate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King, they all, Head and Members, make one Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Body; and this is ſo cleare a truth, that in this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the Act of 17 <hi>Caroli,</hi> it is declared, That the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall not be diſſolved or prorogued but by act of Parliament; but the two Houſes may reſpectively adjourne themſelves; two Houſes &amp; a Parliament are ſeverall things. <hi>Cunct a fidem vero faciunt,</hi> all circumſtances agree to prove this truth. Before the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt, and ſithence to this day, the King is holden Principall, <hi>Caput, &amp; finis,</hi> that is, the beginning, Head and chief end of the Parliament, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the Treatiſe of the manner of holding of Parliaments made before the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt;
<note place="margin">4. <hi>par. Inſtit. pag.</hi> 12.</note> by the Writ of Sumons of Parliament whereby the Treaty and <hi>Parler</hi> in Parliament is to be had with the King onely, by the Common Lau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by the Statute-Law, by the Oath of Supremacy,
<note place="margin">4. <hi>par. Inſtit. pag.</hi> 4.9. 5. <hi>Eli.</hi> c. 1.2.</note> taken at this and every Parliament, it doth manifeſtly appeare, that without the King there can be no colour of a Parliament.</p>
                     <p>How many Votes have they revoked in one Seſſion, yea, and Bills? Was there ever the like done? Nay, is not the conſtant courſe of Parliaments violated and made nothing thereby? They are guarded by Armed-men,
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> divide the publique money among themſelves, and that partie indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to bring in a Forreigne to invade this Land againe: If they be no Parliament, as clearely they are none with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out His Majeſtie, they have no privileges, but doe exerciſe an Arbitrary, Tyrannicall, and Treaſonable power over the people.</p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33168:46"/>
                     <p>By the Law of the Land,
<note place="margin">7. <hi>E.</hi> 4.20. 8. <hi>E.</hi> 4.3. 9. <hi>E.</hi> 4.27. 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7.18. 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.23.</note> when Treaſon or Felony is committed, it is lawfull for every Subject, who ſuſpects the Offender, to apprehend him, and to ſecure him ſo, that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice may be done upon him according to the Law.</p>
                     <p>You ſay, The diſobedience of the Army is a ſad publique preſident, like to conjure up a ſpirit of univerſall diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I pray object not that conjuring up to the Army, whereof you, &amp; the prevailing partie in the Houſes are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; who conjured up the ſpirit of univerſall diſobedience againſt His Majeſtie, your and our onely Supreme Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, But you, and that partie in the two Houſes, and even then, when the houſe of Commons were taking, and did take the ſaid Oath of Supremacy? For the Covenant you mention, it is an Oath againſt the Lawes of the Land, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Petition of Right, deviſed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> wherein the firſt Article is to maintaine the Reformed Religion in the Church of <hi>Scotland:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>pars.</hi> Coll. of Ord. <hi>pag.</hi> 803. Petition of right 3. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>pars.</hi> inſtit. 719.</note> And certainly there is no Subject of the Engliſh Nation doth know what the Scottiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is. I believe the Army tooke not the Covenant: No man by the Law can give an Oath in a new caſe without an Act of Parliament; and therefore the impoſers thereof are very blamable and guiltie of the higheſt Crime.</p>
                     <p>The Writer of theſe <hi>Quaeries</hi> ſeemes to profeſſe the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wes, let him declare what Act of Parliament doth juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the tendring, giving, or taking of the ſaid Oath: he knoweth there is none, he knoweth that all the parts of it are deſtructive of the Lawes and Government to maintaine which the Law of nature &amp; the Law of the Land had obliged them:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mag. Chart. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi cleri,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtatutes. 16. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.10.</note> The Oath of the Covenant makes the Houſes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governours in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, the Oath of Supremacy makes the King ſo, and yet both taken by the ſame perſons, at the ſame time. What credit is to be given to perſons who make nothing of Oathes, and contradict themſelves? How d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e the Covenant and the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy agree? How doth their Proteſtation and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33168:46"/>agree? How doe their Declarations and Oathes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree? The Lord be mercifull to this Land for theſe Oaths.</p>
                     <p>It is a ſad thing to conſider that ſo many gentlemen who profeſſe the lawes, and ſo many worthy men in both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould be ſo tranſported as they are, knowing that the Lawes of the Land from time to time, and in all times, are contrary to all their actions, and that yet they ſhould amuſe themſelves and the people with the word of Parliament, without the King, and with the Covenant; whereas they know they are no Parliament without His Majeſtie, and that Engliſh men throughout the Kingdome ſhould ſweare a Covenant, to preſerve the reformed Religion of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, which they no more know than the Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government of <hi>Preſter Iohn</hi> in <hi>Ethiopia:</hi> if they conſider it, they cannot but diſcerne that this is a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate and impious madneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Be wiſe in time, without the King and the Lawes you will never have one houre of ſafety for your Perſons, Wives, Children or Eſtates: Be good to your ſelves, and to your Poſterities; apply your ſelves to be capable of an Act of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, and of a generall Pardon, and to be able and willing to pay the Souldiery, and to allow a reaſonable liberty for m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> conſciences, and God will bleſſe your endeavours, and the people (to whom you are now very hatefull) will have you in better eſtimation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The third Quarie is thus anſwered.</head>
                     <p>You reſemble the Army to <hi>Iacke Cade</hi> and his Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and you cite the Act of Parliament of 31. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. and that it may appeare who acts the Part of <hi>Iacke Cade,</hi> you and that Party in the two Houſes, or the Army, I thinke it neceſſary to ſet downe the ſaid Act in words at large as followeth.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Whereas <hi>the moſt abominable Tyrant, horrible, odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33168:47"/>and arrant falſe Traytor Iohn Cade,</hi> calling and naming himſelf ſometime <hi>Mortimer,</hi> ſometime Cap. of <hi>Kent,</hi> which name, fame, acts, and feats are to be removed out of the ſpeech and mind of every faithfull Chriſtian man perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, falſely and <hi>traiterouſly purpoſing,</hi> and imagining <hi>the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall deſtruction of the Kings ſaid Perſon, and finall ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Realme, taking upon him Royall power, and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to him the, Kings people in great numbers, by falſe, ſubtle imagined Language, and ſeditiouſly making a ſtirring Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and Inſurrection, under colour of juſtice, for reformation of the Lawes of the ſaid King, robbing, ſtealing, and ſpoiling great part of his faithfull people,</hi> Our ſaid Soveraigne Lord the King conſidering the premiſes, with many other which were more odious to remember, by adviſe and conſent of the Lords aforeſaid, and at the requeſt of the ſaid Commons, and by authority aforeſaid, hath ordained and eſtabliſhed that the ſaid <hi>Iohn Cade</hi> ſhall be reputed; had, named, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared a falſe, Traytour to our Soveraigne Lord the King;</hi> and that all his tyranny, acts, feats; and falſe opinions ſhall be voyded, abated, annulled, deſtroyed; &amp; put out of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance for ever: and that all enditements and all things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending thereof, had and made under the power of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall be like wiſe void, annulled, anated, repealed, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for none: and that the bloud of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> them be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of defiled nor corrupted, but by the authority of the ſaid Parliament cleerely declared for even: and that all endite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in times comming in like caſe under power of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, rebellion and ſtirring had, ſhall be of no Record nor ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but void in Law; and <hi>all the Petitions delivered to the ſaid King in his laſt Parliament, holden at VVeſtminſter, Noveb.</hi> 6. <hi>in the</hi> 29. <hi>of his Raigne, againſt his mind by him not agreed, ſhall be taken and put in oblivion out of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi> undone, voyded, annulled and deſtroyed for ever, as a thing purpoſed againſt God and conſcience, and againſt His Royall Eſtate and preeminence, and alſo diſhonourable and unreaſonable.</p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33168:47"/>
                     <p>Now wee are to examine who hath trod in the ſtep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> you and the preſent prevailing party of the two Houſes <hi>tooke upon them, and doe take all the Royall Power in all things;</hi> ſo did <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> as appeares by the ſaid Act; the Army doe not ſo: They who impriſon the King <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to deſtroy His Perſon</hi> (our impriſoned Kings alwayes
<note n="*" place="margin">Edward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Henry 6. Richard 2.</note> fared ſo) <hi>Jack Cade</hi> did likewiſe ſo purpoſe, but the Army doe not ſo: The ſaid party in the two Houſes <hi>made a ſtirring under colour of Justice for Reformation of the Lawes;</hi> ſo did <hi>Jack Cade:</hi> The Army doe not ſo, but deſire that the Lawes ſhould be obſerved: <hi>Jack Cade le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied Warre againſt the King,</hi> the Army preſerves Him: <hi>Jack Cade</hi> dyed a <hi>Declared Traytor to his Soveraigne Lord the King;</hi> this Army lives to have the glorious true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being reſtorers of their King.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Simon Sudbury</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> was murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Jack Cade i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> William Laud</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> was likewiſe murthered by that party of the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<note place="margin">25 Ed. 3.4. 28 Ed. 3.3. Petition of Right. 3 Car.</note> for that an Ordinance by Law cannot take away any mans life, &amp; his life was taken away by an Ordinance of the two Houſes, the Army had no hand in it. Many miſled by <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> perceiving his Trayterous purpoſes, fell from him; and as that was lawfull, juſt, and Honourable, ſo it is for this Army to adhere to their naturall King, and to indeavour to ſettle the Kingdome againe in the juſt Lawes and Liberties thereof: <hi>London</hi> did then right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily adhere to the King and the Lawes, and not to <hi>Iack Cade</hi> and his ſpecious pretences, and it is hoped they will now ſo doe: By this it appeares, that the Gentlemans Diſcourſe touching <hi>Iack Cade,</hi> faſtens altogether on his party, and cleareth the Army.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To the <hi>IV.</hi> which is ſolved thus.</head>
                     <p>The Arreares of the Army (howbeit it is the leaſt thing they looke after) yet being not paid them, it is by the Law of the Land a ſufficient cauſe to leave and deſert that party
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33168:48"/>in the Houſes: A perſon who ſerves in any kinde, and is not paid his wages, the deſertion of that ſervice is warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table by the Lawes of the Land:
<note place="margin">Pitz. N. B. 25. 9 Ed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.20. 38 H. 6.27. 23 Eliz. Dier 369.</note> You ſay, the Houſes will reforme all things when the Army doth disband; who will beleeve it? Will any beleeve that the ſetling of the Presbytery will doe it? Will any beleeve that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty will paſſe the Propoſitions ſent to Him to <hi>Newcaſtle?</hi> Will any man beleeve that this Kingdome will ever bee quiet, without His Majeſty and the ancient and juſt Lawes? Can the Members of the Army conceive any of them to be ſafe in any thing, without a Pardon from His Majeſty? Have they not ſeene ſome of their Fellows hanged before their eyes, for actions done as Souldiers? Shall the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome have no account of the many Millions received of the Publike Money? Will the Members of the Houſes accuſe themſelves? Shall private and publike Debts bee never paid? Shall the Kingdome lye ever under burthens of Oppreſſion and Tyranny? There is no viſible way to remedy all theſe enormities, but the power of the Army.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To the <hi>V.</hi> which is ſolved thus.</head>
                     <p>The Kingdome hath better aſſurance of Reformation from the Army, then from the Houſes, for that in their Military way they have bin juſt, faithfull &amp; honorable, they have kept their words: That party of the Houſes have bin conſtant to nothing but in dividing the publike Treaſure among themſelves, and in laying burdens upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in breaking all the Oathes, Vowes, and Promiſes they ever made:
<note place="margin">2 &amp; 3 Ed. 6. cap. 2. 11 H 7. cap. 1. Calvins caſe, 7. pars, Cook fol. 11.</note> As the Army hath power, ſo now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to the King, all the Lawes of God, Nature, and Man, are for them, their Armes are juſt, and bleſſed; and the King is bound in Juſtice to reward his Deliverers with Honour, Profit, and meet Liberty of Conſcience.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33168:48"/>
                     <head>To the <hi>VI.</hi> Quare.</head>
                     <p>All the ſixth <hi>Quaere</hi> containes Calumnies caſt upon the Armie; the new elections are againſt all the Lawes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Margin,
<note place="margin">11 H. 4. c. 1. 1 H. 5. c. 1. 8 H. 6. c. 7. 23 H. 6. c. 15.</note> and are againſt the ejection of the old Members: and by this it may be judged, what a Houſe of Commons we have. By the ſaid Lawes it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that if any undue returne be made, the perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned is to continue a Member; the Sherifes puniſhment is two hundred pounds, one to the King, and the other to the partie that is duly elected; impriſonment for a yeare, without Bayle or Mainpriſe: and that perſon who is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duly returned, ſhall ſerve at his owne charge, and have no benefit at the end of the Parliament, by the Writ <hi>de ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione feodorum Militum, Civium &amp; Burgenſium Parliament.</hi> And the tryall of the falſitie of the returne, is to be before the Juſtices of Aſſiſes in the proper Countie, or by Action of Debt in any Court of Record. This condemnes the Committee for undue elections, which hath been practiſed but of late times: for beſides theſe Lawes, it is a Maxime of the Common Law,
<note place="margin">3 Ed. 4.20. 5 Ed. 4.42.</note> an Averment is not receivable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the returne of the Sherife, for his returne is upon Oath which Oath is to be credited in that ſuit wherein the returne is made.</p>
                     <p>The ſaid Statutes condemne elections of ſuch men which were not reſiant and dwelt in the Countie or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs for which they were returned; and any abuſive practiſe of late times to the contrary, is againſt the Law, and ought not to be allowed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To the <hi>VII.</hi> Quaere.</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Quaeriſt</hi> ſaith, That the Votes of the Independents in the Houſes were arbitrarie, exorbitant, and irregular, and that they diſpoſed and fingred more of the common Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure then others: That whole <hi>Quaere,</hi> I believe, is falſe and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33168:49"/>ſlanderous;
<note place="margin">37 E. 5. c. 17.</note> and the Author ought to make it good, or elſe to undergoe the Law of <hi>Talton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>;</hi> which is, to ſuffer ſuch puniſhment, failing of his proofe, as the accured ſhould, in caſe of proofe made.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To the <hi>VIII.</hi> Quaere.</head>
                     <p>This <hi>Quaere</hi> is all minatorie and threatning, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> every part is true: by the deliverance of the King and Kingdome from the bondage of that partie in the two Houſes by the Army, their renowne will be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting; they ſecure themſelves, they content and pleaſe the Kingdome, Citie, and Countrey, as appeares by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to ſee his Majeſtie and the Armie, and their accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations for his Majeſties ſafetie and reſtitution: all which doth evidence to every one of the Armie, how acceptable the intentions of the Armie are to the people of this Land, who have been ſo long inthralled.</p>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> let your Worthineſſe remember your extraction and your Ladies, by the grace and favour of the Prince, to be in the ranke of Nobilitie; remember what honour and glory the preſent Age and all poſteritie will juſtly give to the reſtorer of the King to his Throne, of the Lawes to their ſtrength, and of the afflicted people of this Land to peace: let the Colonels and Commanders under you, and likewiſe your Souldierie, reſt aſſured, that they ſhall not only ſhare in the renowne of this action, but alſo ſhall have ſuch remuneration as their hautie courage and ſo high a vertue doth deſerve: This his Majeſtie can and will doe, the Houſes neither will nor can; and God bleſſe you all, and proſper you.</p>
                     <p>I conclude all, as I have alwayes done: Without an Act of Oblivion, a generall Pardon, the Arreares of the Souldierie payd, and a regard to Libertie of Conſcience, this Kingdome will certainly be ruined.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:33168:49"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
